真实事件改编
14，15…
14, 15...
16，质数
16, prime...
18，质数
18, prime...
21...
22，质数
22, prime...
-西维吉尼亚高中学院
West Virginia Collegiate Institute
是本州黑人能念的最好的学校
is the best school for Negros in the state.
附近只有那里有八年级以上
It's the only school past the eighth grade
的课程
anywhere near here.
等腰三角形
Isosceles.
不等边三角形
Scalene.
正三角形
Equilateral.
菱形
Rhombus.
梯形
Trapezoid.
凯萨琳现在才六年级
Katherine's in the sixth grade.
他们希望她跳级入学
They want to take her early.
四面体
Tetrahedron.
十二面体
Dodecahedron.
他们会提供全额奖学金
They're offering a full scholarship.
你们只要人去就好
All you have to do is get there.
柯曼小姐
Ms. Coleman...
你在黑板上写算式，好吗？
why don't you solve the equation on the board?
我们向教职员
We took up a collection
发起募款
amongst the teachers and such.
虽然金额不大
It's not a lot...
但足够让你们安顿下来
but it's enough to help get you settled in.
桑纳女士，你们真好心
That's more than kind, Ms. Sumner.
如果两个数的乘积是零
If the product of two terms
依照常识判断
is zero then common sense says
两个数中至少有一个是零
at least one of the two terms has to be zero to start with.
如果把所有数移到同一边
So if you move all the terms over to one side,
这个二次方程式因式
you can put the quadratics into a form
分解后
that can be factored...
方程式的那一边
allowing that side of the equation
会等于零
to equal zero.
这样一来就很简单
Once you've done that, it's pretty straightforward
明了了
from there.
我教书这么多年
In all my years of teaching...
从没看过你女儿这么聪明的孩子
I've never seen a mind like the one your daughter has.
凯萨琳
Katherine!
快跟上来，亲爱的
Hurry on now, love.
你们必须去
You have to go.
让妈妈抱你上车
Let Mama tuck you in.
你们必须看到她未来的成就
You have to see what she becomes.
“1961年  维吉尼亚州  汉普顿”
好，发动看看
Okay, try to turn it over now.
凯萨琳？
Katherine?
玛莉
Mary!
有人吗？
Somebody!
凯萨琳
Katherine!
不要再发呆了，快发动车子
Quit staring off into space and turn the damn car over.
知道了
I got it.
我又不是聋子
I'm not deaf.
很难说
I wonder sometimes.
我要发动了
Here it goes.
发动机坏了
Yeah, it's the starter.
一定是启动器的问题
That is definitely the starter.
这个启动器会害我们迟到
This starter is starting to make us late.
我们每天开这辆破车去上班
We are all gonna end up unemployed...
最后一定会丢了工作
riding around in this pile of junk to work every day.
你要走25公里的路也行
You're welcome to walk the 16 miles.
或是坐在巴士后排
Or sit in the back of the bus.
这两种方法我都不要
I won't do neither.
我会搭便车
I'll hitchhike.
姊妹们
Girls.
车子抛锚又不犯法
No crime in a broken-down car.
身为黑人也不犯法
No crime being Negro neither.
别说了，玛莉
Button it up, Mary.
没人想因为你说的话而坐牢
Nobody wants to go to jail behind your mouth.
我尽量，蜜糖
I'll do my best, sugar.
“州警局”
这里不是抛锚的好地方
Not a great place for three of y'all be having car trouble.
我们也没得选，警官
We didn't pick the place, Officer. It picked us.
你在顶嘴吗？
You being disrespectful?
不，长官
No, sir.
你们有证件吗？
You have identification on you?
有的，长官    -有，长官
Yes, sir. Yes, sir.
我们正要去上班
We're just on our way to work...
在朗里
at Langley.
太空总署，长官
NASA, sir.
我们的工作是大量的计算
We do a great deal of the calculating.
让火箭飞入太空
Getting our rockets into space.
你们三个都是    -对，长官
All three of you? Yes, sir.
是的，长官
Yes, Officer.
太空总署
NASA.
很了不起嘛
Now that's something.
我不知道他们还雇用…
I had no idea they hired...
太空计划的成员有不少是女性
There are quite a few women working in the space program.
该死的俄国佬正在监视我们
Damn Russians are watching us right now.
那些史普尼克卫星
Sputniks.
你们见过太空人吗？
You girls ever meet those astronauts?
水星计划的七人？
Mercury Seven?
当然
Absolutely.
见过，长官，我们是同事
Uh, yes, sir. We work with those gentlemen all the time.
他们是国家的希望
Those boys are the best we got. I'm sure of that.
是的    -没错
Yeah. Yeah.
我们要比共产党先把人送上太空
We gotta get a man up there before the commies do.
对    -一定要
Yes. Absolutely.
整个国家都靠他们了
Whole damn country's counting on them.
绝对如此
That's for certain.
但我们在路边抛锚
Hard being of service broken down
就帮不上忙了
on the side of the road, though.
是啊
Right, right.
你们需要拖车还是什么吗？
Well, do y'all need a tow or something?
谢谢你，警官，我想我能处理
No, thank you, Officer. I think I got it.
把那个给我
Just give me my...
我只要绕过启动器就好
Just need to bypass the starter.
她很行的
She's good at this stuff.
好女孩
Whoo! Attagirl.
我们弄好了
We're all set.
至少我能帮你们开路
Well, hell, least I can do is give y'all an escort.
我想你们应该迟到了
I imagine you're running late to work.
不，长官，我们不想麻烦你
No, sir. We wouldn't wanna bother you.
那太好了，警官
That would be wonderful, Officer.
非常谢谢你，长官
Thank you so much, sir.
跟着我吧
Follow me.
我来开
I'm driving.
桃乐斯快点，以免他改变主意
Hurry up, Dorothy, before he changes his mind.
我们来了    -等一下
- We're coming. - Hold your horses.
赞    -玛莉，开慢点
Yes! Whoa, slow down, Mary!
慢点，你太近了
Mary, slow down! You're too close!
-别吵，他说跟着他
Be quiet. He said to follow him.
他没说贴着他
He didn't mean up his behind!
老天，这到底是怎么回事
Dear Lord, I don't even know where to begin!
我告诉你是怎么回事
Oh, I'll tell you where to begin.
三个黑人女性追着白人警官的车
Three Negro women are chasing a white police officer
开在维吉尼亚州汉普顿的公路上
down the highway in Hampton, Virginia...
时间是1961年
1961.
各位女士，这是神注定的奇蹟
Ladies, that there is a God-ordained miracle.
明天我要搭巴士  玛莉
And, tomorrow, I'm riding the bus.
我正要过去
I'm moving over
我在通道
I'm on a sidewalk
我要过去了
I'm going over
升空顺利，轨道稳定
Lift off is good. Trajectory is stable.
给我看
Show me.
不，要详细的
No, exactly.
北纬40.349110度
40.349110 degrees North.
上升角度46.56度
Ascent angle 46. 56.
时速接近11,909公里
Approaching 7,400 miles per hour.
118秒
118 seconds.
推进器分离
Boosters have disengaged.
第二阶段成功
Second stage success.
史普尼克4号进入轨道
Korabl-Sputnik 4 is orbital.
确认进入轨道
Orbital entry is established.
确认俄国进入轨道
Russian orbital entry is established.
我是吉姆韦伯
Jim Webb.
是，总统先生
Yes, Mr. President.
我们绝对是，先生
We certainly are, sir.
他们成功进入一个轨道
Uh, it looks like they've achieved
可能两个
at least one orbit, maybe two.
小狗查努卡准备再次上太空
Chernushka is ready to go again.
我们英勇的太空旅行同志伊凡也是
So is our comrade, Ivan, a brave space traveler.
我们已经证明生命能在太空中维持
We have proven life can be sustained in space.
也将是最早送人类上太空的国家
Now we will be first to send a human.
一只该死的狗和该死的假人
A damn dog and a damn mannequin.
然后160万吨的RDS-37热核弹头
And then, a 1.6 megaton RDS-37 thermonuclear warhead...
就会直接丢在艾荷华州首府中央
drops down in the middle of Des Moines.
这个结论跳得太快了，长官
Well, that's a pretty big jump, sir.
什么？
What?
因为…    -他是哪根葱？
Just that... Who the hell is he?
他是主任工程师保罗史塔佛，长官
Paul Stafford, our lead engineer, Mr. Webb.
我想他的意思是…
I think what he meant to say...
您刚刚的推测，至少就我们的计算
is that speculation, at least on our side of the equation...
在定义上而言…
by definition can be...
是有一点点危险的
just a little dangerous.
危险？
Dangerous?
你懂什么是危险吗，史塔佛先生？
You know what's dangerous, Mr. Stafford?
无所作为和犹豫不决
Inaction and indecision.
俄国佬有间谍卫星
The Russians have a spy satellite
绕着地球转
lapping the planet,
谁知道他们偷拍了什么照片
taking pictures of God knows what!
总统要求我们立刻做出回应
The President is demanding an immediate response.
不能再拖了
No more delay. Alan Shepard, John Glenn,
不管是谁都没差
your uncle Bob, it doesn't matter.
把人弄上去就对了，哈里逊
Get us up there, Harrison.
要是太空计划再没有进展
We can't justify a space program
我们就站不住脚了
that doesn't put anything in space.
刚刚感觉怎么样，保罗？
How'd that feel in there, Paul?
你觉得自己有让长官了解了吗？
You think you enlightened the administrator?
不，我觉得他不了解
No, he didn't look enlightened to me.
你觉得他了解了吗，山姆？
He look enlightened to you, Sam?
没有那种感觉
Not particularly.
我告诉你
And just so you know,
他刚刚说的没错
he's not wrong about what he said in there.
你也知道吧？
You know that, right?
既然能上去了
Because now that they can get up there,
下一步就是炸弹了
a bomb will follow.
我们所有的好点子都是这样
It's what happens to all our good ideas.
我想他们也不例外…东西呢？
I imagine theirs too. Where's...
机器呢？
Where's the machine?
随时会到，哈里逊先生
Any day now, Mr. Harrison.
随时会到    -是，长官
Any day now. Yes, sir.
那间公司叫什么名字？
What's it called? The initials.
缩写是IBM
The IBM.
国际商业机器公司
International Business Machines.
太空是一种商业活动
Space is a business.
我需要数学家
I need a mathematician.
我会另外提出要求，长官
I'll put in another request, sir.
又是要求，我的老天
"Another request." Jesus Christ.
整栋楼里没有一个人…
We don't have a single person in this entire building
能处理解析几何吗？
that can handle analytic geometry?
据我所知没有
That's what I've been told.
说点好消息吧，茹丝
Tell me something else, Ruth...
像是俄国人
like we're gonna find such a person
在月球插旗前
before the Russians plant a flag
我们会找到这个人
on the damn moon.
真的很开心
A real good time.
葛洛莉雅，你去四号楼的工程组
All right, Gloria.
“有色人种计算组”
You'll be with engineering, building four.
各位女士
Ladies, ladies.
你要是迟到就分不到案子
If you're tardy, you don't get an assignment.
你分不到案子
If you don't get an assignment,
就没有工作
you don't have a job.
伊莲娜
Eleanor.
资料简化，202大楼
Data Reduction, building 202.
资料简化？
Data Reduction?
你想去和磁性电浆动力学作伴
You're welcome to join the charmers
也行
in Magnetoplasma Dynamics.
不了，女士
Oh, no, ma'am.
谢谢，资料简化很好
Thank you. Data Reduction is just fine.
玛莉    -我在
Mary. Present.
水星计划的原型要开始测试了
The Mercury Seven prototype has arrived for testing.
兹林斯基先生要你…
Mr. Zielinski's requesting you
长期负责这项任务
for permanent assignment.
你说真的吗？
Are you serious?
动作快
Get moving.
感谢耶稣
Ooh, thank you, Jesus.
Thank you, Jesus!
玛莉，你不用说出来
Oh, thank you. Mary, Mary. Keep it inside.
对喔，抱歉，桃乐斯
Okay. I'm sorry, Dor.
好了，蕾特女士
All right, Ms. Late.
你也要支援东侧计算组
You will also be supporting the east group.
米契尔女士
Mrs. Mitchell.
今天早上的动作要特别快，女孩们
We're on double-time this morning, girls.
这些东西午餐前要算出来
I need these calculations before lunch.
太空任务团队需要计算人员，尽快
Space Task Group needs a computer, ASAP.
要能处理解析几何的人
Someone with a handle on analytic geometry.
东侧计算组找不到人
We can't fill that position out of the east group.
长期还是临时？
Permanent or temp?
一切都是临时，桃乐斯
Everything's temporary, Dorothy.
你有人能用？
You have someone?
我有，女士
Yes, ma'am.
凯萨琳是适合人选
Katherine's the gal for that.
她能处理任何数字运算
She can handle any numbers you put in front of her.
我会查一下她的资格
I'll check her credentials.
没想到我居然会来这地方
Didn't think I'd come all the way down here.
这边，把那些东西送出去
Here. Finish passing those out.
是，女士
Yes, ma'am.
米契尔女士
Mrs. Mitchell.
打扰一下…
If I could...
我的主管申请，女士
My application for supervisor, ma'am.
他们是否还考虑
Was just wondering if they're still considering me
让我担任主管职？
for that position.
对
Yes.
官方说法是没有
Well, the official word is no.
他们不打算为有色人种组安排主管
They're not assigning a permanent supervisor for the colored group.
我能问为什么吗？
May I ask why?
我不知道为什么
I don't know why.
我没有问为什么
I didn't ask why.
我们需要主管，女士
We need a supervisor, ma'am.
珍森小姐生病以后就没有主管了
We haven't had one since Miss Jansen got sick.
都快要一年了
It's been almost a year.
目前运作也没什么问题啊
Things are working just fine as is.
因为我在做主管的工作
I'm doing the work of a supervisor.
太空总署就是这么回事
Well, that's NASA for you.
做火箭急得很，升官慢得很
Fast with rocket ships, slow with advancement.
把那些轨道计算弄好吧
Get those trajectory calcs worked out.
红石测试需要那些数字
We need them for the Redstone test.
一马赫风洞测试，发射前一分钟
Mach one tunnel test. T-minus one minute.
你的命比鞋子重要吧
No shoe is worth your life.
等一下
One moment.
发射前倒数，10、9
T-minus 10, 9...
8...
7...
6、5、4
6, 5, 4...
关掉
Shut it down.
如果把外壳从平滑改成波浪状
If we alter the exterior from smooth to corrugated...
座舱可能会更稳定
the capsule might have more stability.
但是重回大气层时会增加摩擦力
But the friction, it is under during re-entry...
大部分的挡板腐蚀…
Most shield erosion occurs
都在后端，后推进器附近的地方
on the posterior side abutting the retro-boosters.
结论呢？
Conclusion?
最靠近推进器的地方
The area closest to the boosters
最接近热源
is closest to the heat.
加上重返大气层时温度会升高
Coupled with rising temperature on re-entry...
接触面会变软
the contact softens.
我们可以考虑螺栓以外
We could consider another fastener
的固定方式
other than the bolts.
对
Yes.
工程训练计划
There is another opening
还有一个名额
in the Engineer Training Program.
平头铆钉可以减少风阻力
Flat head rivets would reduce wind drag.
有工程师头脑的人
Mary, a person with engineer's mind
应该做工程师
should be an engineer.
你不能一辈子都在做计算
You can't be a computer the rest of your life.
兹林斯基先生…
Mr. Zielinski...
我是黑人女性
I'm a Negro woman.
我不会痴人说梦
I'm not gonna entertain the impossible.
我是父母死于纳粹集中营的
And I'm a Polish Jew
波兰裔犹太人
whose parents died in a Nazi prison camp.
现在我头顶上这艘太空船
Now I'm standing beneath a spaceship
将会载着太空人飞向星空
that's going to carry an astronaut to the stars.
我想可以说我们正在活出不可能
I think we can say we are living the impossible.
我问你，如果
Let me ask you...
你是白人男性
if you were a white male,
会想当工程师吗？
would you wish to be an engineer?
我不用想，因为我会已经是了
I wouldn't have to. I'd already be one.
裙子长度必须过膝
Skirts must be worn past the knee.
穿毛衣比宽松上衣好
Sweaters are preferred to blouses.
除了简单的珍珠项链外
No jewelry.
不能戴首饰
A simple pearl necklace is the exception.
你的主管是艾尔哈里逊先生
Your supervisor is Mr. Al Harrison,
他是太空任务团队的主持人
Director of the Space Task Group.
你要写研究报告，检查计算结果等
You'll write research, proof calculations, so forth.
只有哈里逊先生问你时你才能说话
Do not talk to Mr. Harrison unless he talks to you.
大部分计算人员都撑不了几天
Not many computers last more than a few days.
这几个月他已经赶走十几个了
He's been through a dozen in as many months.
快跟上
Come on, keep up.
这里步调很快
Things move fast around here.
“太空任务团队”
你的通行证
Your clearance.
这里从来没有黑人，凯萨琳
They've never had a colored in here before, Katherine.
不要让我丢脸
Don't embarrass me.
这个昨天没有清
This wasn't emptied last night.
抱歉，我不是…
I'm sorry, I'm not the...
工友
custodian.
抱歉，女士
Excuse me, ma'am.
我是哈里逊先生的计算人员
Mr. Harrison's computer reporting.
去后面的桌子，我等等就交办工作
Take the desk in the back. I'll get you work in a bit.
别期望哈里逊先生热烈欢迎你
Mr. Harrison won't warm up to you. Don't expect it.
做好你的工作，别引人注意
Do your work, keep your head down.
谢谢你
Thank you.
快去把东西放好
Go on. Get settled.
保罗
Paul.
为什么防热罩的挡板
Why are we still losing shingles
还是会掉？
off the heat shield?
我们正在设计座舱原型，艾尔
We're working with a prototype of the capsule, Al.
舱盖尺寸是三分之一…
Its lid is one third the size of what it's going...
我知道
I get that.
那个价值百万的风扇该怎么办？
So, what do we do with our million dollar fan, Karl?
关掉吗？    -不，艾尔，我不…
Turn it down? No, Al. I don't think...
我是开玩笑的
It was a joke.
保罗，如果防热挡板掉了
Paul, if the heat shield comes off...
你想我们的太空人会怎么样？
what do you think happens to our astronaut?
我知道
I know.
所以我们得想办法解决，对吧？
So we're gonna come up with a solve, right?
是的，我们正在努力
Yes, sir. We're working on it.
茹丝，计算人员的事怎么样了？
Ruth, what's the status on that computer?
她就在你后面，哈里逊先生
She's right behind you, Mr. Harrison.
她能处理解析几何吗？
Does she handle Analytic Geometry?
绝对可以，而且她会说话
Absolutely. And she speaks.
是，先生，我会
Yes, sir. I do.
会哪一个？    -都会
Which one? Both.
几何学和说话
Geometry and speaking.
茹丝，NRuth, get me the...
给我…\
You think you...
你能算出这份资料
You think you can find me the Frenet frame
的空间曲线吗？
for this data?
用格拉姆施…
Using the Gram-Schmidt...
-正交化演算法
Orthogonalization algorithm. Yes, sir.
比欧几里得座标来得好
I prefer it over Euclidean coordinates.
好，很好
Okay, good.
很好，下班前给我
Good, then I'm gonna need it by the end of the day.
好的
Yes.
我还要你不时
I'm also gonna ask you
检查一下
to check Mr. Stafford's math
史塔佛先生和其他人
as well as others' on this floor
的数学计算
from time to time.
那个我行的，艾尔
I can handle that, Al.
我知道你行，我确定他们都行
I'm sure you can, Paul. I'm sure they all can.
但如果真是那样
But if that were the case
防热罩的挡板
shingles wouldn't be flying off the heat shield,
就不会脱落了吧？
now would they?
打扰一下，大家听我说
Excuse me, could I have everyone's attention
好吗？
for a moment?
谢谢
Thank you.
我要声明
Just to be clear...
水星计划的七人在14天后会来受训
in 14 days, the Mercury Seven will be here for training.
我非常肯定他们一定会…
And I have no doubt in my mind that they're going to be
问我们关于工作的问题
asking us questions about our work.
我想这是很合理的
I think that's pretty reasonable
毕竟我们要把人放上飞弹
given we're putting a human on top of a missile,
发射到太空里
shooting him into space,
而且没有前例可循
and it's never been done before.
因为这是前所未见的
Because it's never been done,
我们现在的所作所为都非常重要
everything we do between now and then is gonna matter.
对他们的妻子…
It's gonna matter to their wives...
对他们的孩子都很重要
to their children.
对整个国家都很重要
I believe it's gonna matter to the whole damn country.
这个太空任务团队会被大肆宣传
So this Space Task Group will be as advertised.
美国最厉害的工程师及科学家
America's greatest engineering and scientific minds
一定不反对自己的工作接受检验
are not gonna have a problem
是不是，保罗？
with having their work checked. Are they, Paul?
是的，长官
No, sir.
很好，让我们一致阿们同意，妈的
Good. So let's have an amen, damn it.
阿们
Amen.
阿们    -阿们
Amen!
好了
All right.
我的数字绝对没错
My numbers are spot on.
我会验算的，先生，没问题
I will double check them, sir. No problem.
这样我不能…    -检查你能看的范围
I'm not gonna be able to... Work on what you can read.
其他部分是机密，你不能看
The rest is classified. You don't have clearance.
这些是哈里逊先生给我的数字
These are the numbers Mr. Harrison gave me.
是，我要…    -抱歉
Yes, I'm absolutely... Excuse me.
请问洗手间在哪里？
May I ask where the ladies' room is?
抱歉，我不清楚你的洗手间在哪里
Sorry. I have no idea where your bathroom is.
是，先生
Yes, sir.
Uh, yes, sir.
“女用洗手间”
“太空总署”
♪ Summertime in Virginia was an oven
♪ All the kids eating ice cream with their cousins
♪ I was studyin' while you was playing the dozens
♪ Don't act like you was there when you wasn't
♪ Runnin' from the man
♪ Runnin' from the badge
♪ Don't act like you was there when you wasn't
♪ Runnin' toward our plans
♪ And the judges hands
♪ Don't act like you was there when you wasn't
♪ I know they say you crawl before you walk
“有色人种女用洗手间”
♪ But in my mind I already jog
♪ If I stand still I cannot get far
♪ They want the moon I'm on Mars
♪ Sometime my mind dives deep when I'm runnin'
♪ Together we'll fly But no more runnin'
茹丝
Ruth!
什么事，哈里逊先生？
Yes, Mr. Harrison?
茹丝，算数字的女生呢？
Ruth, where's that girl with the numbers?
去…休息
On a... break.
我们有休息时间吗？
We take breaks now?
♪ Sometime my mind dives deep When I'm runnin'
“西侧计算组”
♪ I don't want no free ride
♪ I'm just sick and tired of runnin'
♪ Together we fly But no more runnin'
我的天，你去哪里了？
My God, where have you been?
你算完了吗？
Are you finished yet?
差不多，他说下班前完成
Almost. He said by the end of the day.
这里说下班前意思是昨天前
The end of the day around here was yesterday.
先做那些
I need those done first.
他要你先做这些    -好
He wants those done first. Okay.
快点
Get going.
抱歉
I'm sorry about that.
有人在算了
Somebody's working on it right now.
“查克坚果咖啡”
哈里逊先生
Mr. Harrison.
喔，放着就好
Yeah. Uh, Just set it... You know.
史塔佛的防热罩计算结果呢？
And Stafford's heat shield calcs?
我很难确定，先生
It's hard to be sure, sir.
很难确定
Hard to be sure.
你知道我们在做什么吗？
You know what we're doing here?
想办法把人送上太空，先生
Trying to put a man into space, sir.
没错
That's right.
没错，所以那些可以丢了
That's right. So you can throw that in the trash.
您说什么？
Excuse me?
我说那可以丢了
I said you can throw it away.
给我
Here.
我不是污辱你的工作
It's not an insult to your work.
只是这些都过时了
It's just obsolete.
这里的节奏就是这么快
That's how fast things are moving around here.
如果需要道歉，我会整天都在道歉
If I said I was sorry, I'd be saying it all day.
我要你
What I'm asking you to do,
和这里的每个人做的…
what I'm asking everyone in that room...
这里所有天才要做的
all my geniuses...
是跳脱眼前的数字
is to look beyond the numbers.
观察数字的周围
To look around them.
看穿这些数字
Through them.
找出我们还没想到的问题的答案
For answers to questions we don't even know to ask.
找到还不存在的数学
Math that doesn't yet exist.
因为没有这些，我们哪也去不了
Because without it, we're not going anywhere.
我们只能留在地面上
We're staying on the ground.
我们飞不进太空，无法绕行地球
We're not flying into space. We're not circling the Earth.
绝对无法登陆月球
And we're certainly not touching the Moon.
但在我心里…
And in my mind...
在我心里，我已经到月球了
In my mind, I'm already there.
你呢？
Are you?
是的，长官
Yes, sir.
很好
Good.
因为我不需要
Because I don't need another smart girl
另一个聪明的计算机
with an adding machine.
我可以走了吗，先生？
Can I go, sir?
可以，走吧
Yeah, go.
你可以走了
Yes, you can go.
我们等了好久，下次你搭巴士吧
We've been waiting for hours. Next time, you take the bus.
她心情不好
She's in a mood.
♪ People talkin' tryin' to break us up
♪ Why won't they let us be?
♪ Brick and stones may break my bones
♪ But talk don't bother me
♪ I've been abused
♪ In my heart
我这十年没迟到过一天
I haven't been late one day in 10 years.
没有请过病假，没有抱怨过
Haven't been out sick. Haven't complained.
准时交出工作
My work's on time.
做得又正确又好
It's done right. It's done well.
不公平，这就是事实
It's not fair, that's a fact.
不公平的是
What's not fair is having
我要负主管的责任
the responsibility of a supervisor...
但没有头衔没有薪资水准
- but not the title or the pay. - Mmm.
还要看着你们升职
Watching you two move on.
不要误会了
Now, don't get me wrong.
任何人升职都是提升我们的地位
Any upward movement is movement for us all.
只是我没有任何进展
Just isn't movement for me.
老实说，桃乐斯
Truth be told, Dorothy...
我不知道自己能不能适应那里
I don't even know if I can keep up in that room.
一周后我就会回到计算组了
I'll be back with the computers in a week.
或是直接丢了这份工作
Or out of a job entirely.
拜托
Oh, please.
你是这里数学最好的人
You're better with the numbers than anyone in there,
你也知道
Katherine, and you know it.
你只要笔动得跟脑袋一样快
Just make that pencil move as fast as your mind does...
你就没问题了
you'll be fine.
然后你给我放尊重一点
And you, have some respect.
脚不要放在仪表板
Get your damn feet off my dashboard.
又不是你家客厅
This isn't your living room.
我听起来就像主管，对吧？
I sound like a supervisor, don't I?
刻薄又严厉的老主管
A mean old salty one.
而且大权在握，毫无疑问
Riddled with authority, no question.
别想跟范恩女士耍花招
You don't mess with Mrs. Vaughan.
音乐大声一点
Turn that music up.
晚安，凯萨琳
Good night, Katherine.
再见，小凯
Bye, Kat.
晚安，两位
Good night, ladies.
明天见    -再见
- See you in the morning. - Bye.
宝贝，你回来了
Hey, baby.
妈妈，我回来了
Hello, Mama.
我正想通报国民警卫队呢
I was fixing to call the National Guard.
对不起，妈妈，我有新工作
Sorry, Mama. New assignment.
是太空任务团队
Space Task Group.
我的天，听起来好重要
Oh, my word. That sounds important.
是升职吗？
It's a promotion?
应该算小升职吧
It might be a slight promotion.
你想要这份工作吧？
But you want the job, right?
应该是
I think so.
虽然有点挑战性…
It's a challenge, but...
没有你应付不来的，凯萨琳
It's nothing you can't handle, Katherine.
谢谢，妈妈
Thank you, Mama.
他们都睡了吗？
Are they asleep yet?
他们假装睡了
They're pretending to be.
你在做什么？    -我不…
- What are you doing? - I don't...
他们装得不够好
They're not pretending well enough.
康斯坦丝
Constance!
谢谢妈妈，我爱你
Thank you, Mama. Love you.
这是我的床    -不是
This is my bed. No.
下去啦
Get off!
回你的床去，我比较大    -不要
Go back to yours! I'm oldest! No.
你在干嘛？    -下去啦
- What are you doing? - Get off!
你们在做什么？
What are you doing?
乔乐黛可以自己睡，不公平
It's not fair how Joylette gets to sleep by herself
她只不过年纪最大而已
because she's the oldest.
这样很公平    -不公平
Yes, it is fair. No, it's not.
很公平    -才不是
- Yes, it is. - Nuh-uh.
康斯坦丝，凯西，坐下
Constance, Kathy, sit.
我知道…
Now, I understand...
你们想长大，有自己的空间
you want to be grown and have your own space.
所以睡在乔乐黛的位置
So, whoever sleeps in that bed,
的小孩
in Joylette's place...
还需要洗碗
will also do the dishes...
拿垃圾去倒
take out the trash...
还有乔乐黛负责的所有家事
and do all of Joylette's chores.
那算了，不用换了
That's okay. Never mind.
跟她睡也没那么糟
Yeah, she's not so terrible to share with.
好
Okay.
别再让我回家还看到
Then don't let me come home
你们这样吵了
and find you like this again, you hear me?
你们应该早就睡着了
You're supposed to been asleep a long time ago.
我们只是想跟你说晚安
We just wanted to say goodnight.
你去上班300个小时了
You've been gone for 300 hours.
我知道，我现在做的是全职工作
I know. I work a full-time job now.
你们都知道的啊
You all know that.
我要当妈妈，还有爸爸
I have to be Mommy and Daddy.
我和你们一样想你们爸爸
I miss your father just as much as anyone.
他和天使在一起
He's with the angels.
对，他和所有天使在一起
Yes, he's with all the angels.
而且看顾着我们
And he's watching over us.
分分秒秒，知道吗？
Every minute, okay?
所以我们要坚强
That's why we have to be strong.
好吗？
All right?
好，妈妈    -好，妈妈
Yes, Mama. Yes, Mama.
你们都休息了，好吗？
Y'all get some rest, okay?
妈妈？
Mama?
什么事，宝贝？
Yes, baby?
俄国人打算攻击我们吗？
Are the Russians fixin' to attack us?
你从哪里听来的？
Where'd you get that from?
我们今天都要躲在桌子下
We had to hide under our desks today...
弯着身体缩在一起
all scrunched up.
好，宝贝，那是演习
Okay, baby, that's called a drill.
意思是先练习
It means, uh...
这样万一发生什么事
you practice safety
才能安全
just in case something happens.
我们其实也不知道他们想干嘛
Truth is, we don't know what they're doing up there.
你也要上太空吗？
You going to space, too?
没有，宝贝
No, baby.
但我会尽我所能
But I'm going to do what I can
帮那些勇敢的人上太空，就是这样
to help those brave men get there. Yes, I am.
你想的话也可以飞到太空，妈妈
You could fly up to space if you wanted to, Mama.
你可以当太空人
You could be an astronaut.
这是你画的？    -对，妈妈
Did you draw this? Yes, Mama.
那是我吗？
Is that me?
对啊
Mmm-hmm.
你看到了吗？
You see this?
我的天啊
Oh, my goodness.
我爱你，宝贝
I love you, baby.
我知道
I know.
过来
Come here.
好，真的要睡觉了喔
All right. Now this time really go to bed.
好吗？
Okay?
我爱你们    -晚安
I love y'all. Good night.
晚安
Good night. Good night, Mama.
我很喜欢你的画，宝贝
I love my picture, baby.
感谢主
Thank you, Lord.
赞美神    -赞美神
- Praise God! - Praise God!
哈利路亚    -哈利路亚
Hallelujah! Hallelujah!
哈利路亚
Hallelujah.
赞美神
Praise God...
改变即将来临
that change is coming.
从南方基督教领袖会
From the Southern Christian Leadership Conference...
到好牧师金恩博士
to the good reverend Dr. King...
阿门    -哈利路亚
Amen! Hallelujah!
到坐在北卡莱纳州餐厅抗议
...to the students sitting in at lunch counters
的学生
in North Carolina.
没错    -是，先生
That's right. Yes, sir.
祂毫无保留地信任我们
His faith in us has no limit.
美善的主让我们的女性
The good Lord has our very own women
建造太空船
working on rocket ships.
我们还有国民警卫队
And we have National Guardsmen
扞卫我们的自由
defending our freedom.
让我们大声赞美吉姆强生上校
Give a shout of praise for Colonel Jim Johnson.
神的恩惠带他回乡
Returning home, by the grace of God
在汉普顿这里成立
to set up a National Guard unit
国民警卫队
right here in Hampton.
一起说哈利路亚吧
Can I get a hallelujah in here?
哈利路亚
Hallelujah!
我不懂
I just don't understand.
I don't understand it.
我不想再讲一次，好吗？
I don't wanna talk about this again, okay?
女性工程师？
A female engineer?
我们是黑人
We're Negro, baby.
你知道那是不可能的
Ain't no such thing. Understand it.
那边不一样，里凡
It's not like that there, Levi.
你不能申请获得自由
You can't apply for freedom.
受压迫的人必须争取自由
Freedom is never granted to the oppressed.
你要提出要求、去争取
It's got to be demanded. Taken.
不要跟我说那些口号
Stop quoting your slogans at me.
要达到目标的方法不只一种
There is more than one way to achieve something.
我不想吃蔬菜
I don't want any greens.
我说过不要插嘴吧？
Hey. I tell you about interrupting?
吃吃看这个，宝贝
Here. Try this, baby.
好
Yes.
小孩就是要吃蔬菜
You're gonna eat them greens, too.
小孩必须吃掉自己的蔬菜
Kids need to eat their vegetables.
你如果在家就会知道这件事
You'd know that if you was ever home.
你最好别再说了，里凡杰克森
You better settle down, Levi Jackson.
除非你想让我
Unless you want this female's mind,
在这里说出真心话
right here, in front of everybody.
我的意思是…
All I'm saying...
你别白费力气
don't play the fool.
我不想看到你受伤
I don't wanna see you get hurt.
太空总署从来没有善待过你们
NASA's never ever given you guys your due.
多拿两个学位
Having a couple of extra degrees
也不会改变什么
ain't gonna change that.
争取人权的方法不一定文明
Civil rights ain't always civil.
我也不想吃蔬菜了
I don't want any greens either.
不要顶嘴，小女孩
No lip, little miss.
哥哥有吃，你也要吃
Your brother gets them, and so do you.
我听说他打算留在这区
I hear he's planning on staying in the area.
是吗？那很好
Oh, yeah? Well, that's good for him.
凯萨琳，过去发展第二春啊
Katherine, go find your way over there.
吉姆上校真是秀色可餐
That Colonel Jim is a tall glass of water.
的确是
That he is.
又高又壮，还有权威
Tall, strong, commanding.
我打赌他晚上也是一样
And I bet he's like that day and night.
玛莉，今天是礼拜日
Mary, it's Sunday.
拜托你收敛一点
Please have some shame.
我才不要
I will not.
他在朝我们这里笑
Hmm, I think he's smiling over here.
他在对你笑
At you.
我才不会回应
Well I'm not smiling back.
你要对他笑
Yes, you are. Oh, child.
孩子，你嘴都合不拢了    -我没有
You are all teeth right now. I am not.
过来这里
Come over here.
他要过来了
He's coming over.
他为什么要过来？
Now, why would he be doing that?
因为玛莉跟他挥手    -不要
- 'Cause Mary's waving at him. - No!
我还没准备好    -太晚了，快梳头
Ladies, I'm not ready. It's too late. Fix your hair.
你好，上校
Hello, Colonel.
我是桃乐斯范恩
I'm Dorothy Vaughan.
她是玛莉杰克森，她先生是里凡
That's Mary Jackson. I believe you met her husband, Levi.
我认识里凡，很高兴认识你们
Yes, ma'am. Good to meet y'all.
这是凯萨琳哥柏女士
And Mrs. Katherine Goble.
她目前单身，是寡妇
She's not married. She's a widow...
有三个美丽的女儿
...with three beautiful little girls.
她们都很乖
So well behaved.
我们都说她们是地上的天使
Angels on earth is what we like to call them.
桃乐斯，要吃派吗？
Dorothy, slice of pie?
我很想吃
I'd love one.
借过
Excuse me.
你刚刚才吃过派
You already have a slice of pie...
-又怎样
Uh-huh.
我要帮三个孩子装点食物
I was just, uh, fixing my three babies some plates...
我来帮你
Let me help you.
好啊
Sure.
水果沙拉，对
Fruit salad. Mmm-hmm.
牧师提到你在太空总署负责计算
Pastor mentioned you're a computer at NASA.
是的
Yes.
工作内容是什么？
What's that entail? Oh.
我们做必要的数学计算
We calculate the mathematics necessary
实现太空计划的发射和着陆
to enable launch and landing for the space program.
听起来很严肃
That's pretty heady stuff.
是的
Yes, it is.
他们让女人处理这种…
They let women handle that sort of...
我不是那个意思
That's not what I mean.
你是什么意思？
What do you mean?
我只是很惊讶这么…
I'm just surprised that something so...
困难的事…
taxing... Mmm-hmm.
强生先生
Mr. Johnson.
如果我是你，现在就会闭嘴
If I were you, I'd quit talking right now.
我无意冒犯你
I didn't mean no disrespect.
我是西维吉尼亚…
I will have you know
州立大学研究所
I was the first Negro female student
首位黑人女学生
at West Virginia University Graduate School.
我每天
On any given day...
都在分析…
I analyze the manometer levels
压力计排气量、摩擦力、速率资料
for air displacement, friction, and velocity
计算一万多笔的
and compute over 10,000 calculations
三角函数与平方根
by cosine, square root...
最近还在算解析几何
and, lately, analytic geometry.
用手算
By hand.
西侧计算组有20位聪明的
There are 20 bright, highly capable
黑人女性
Negro women in the West Computing Group.
为国家贡献己力让我们引以为荣
And we're proud to be doing our part for the country.
所以，是的
So, yes.
女性能在太空总署做事，强生先生
They let women do some things at NASA, Mr. Johnson.
而且不是因为我们穿裙子
And it's not because we wear skirts.
是因为我们戴眼镜
It's because we wear glasses.
祝你今天愉快
Have a good day.
“太空总署”
史考特，欢迎来到朗里
Scott, welcome to Langley.
欢迎来到朗里    -欢迎
Welcome to Langley. Welcome.
真高兴你们来了
Good to have you here, gentlemen.
谢谢
Thank you.
那是艾伦薛帕，美国海军飞行员
That's Alan Shepard, U.S. Navy pilot.
他会是第一个进入太空的人
He could be the first man in space.
那是史考特卡本特、华特舒拉
And that's Scott Carpenter and Walter Schirra...
都是海军飞行员
also Navy pilots.
大概都180公分，80公斤
All under 5'11", 180 pounds.
智商超过130
IQs over 130. Mmm.
而且长得帅一定也是条件之一
And handsome must be a requirement too.
你怎么能对那些白人抛媚眼？
How could you possibly be ogling these white men?
我有平等的权利
It's equal rights.
看各种肤色的帅哥
I have the right to see fine in every color.
那是约翰格伦  他是唯一的海军陆战队飞行员
And that's John Glenn. He's the only Marine Corps pilot.
各位先生，这里还有很多要看的
Gentlemen, if we may, much to see around here.
可是我们还没握完所有人的手
Well, heck, we haven't shaken all the hands yet.
我们的行程很赶，上校
We have a fairly tight itinerary, Colonel.
茹丝，没关系
Ruth, he's fine.
他要过来了    -看着前方
He's coming this way. Look straight ahead.
我正看着他
I'm looking right at him.
各位女士，我不想不告而别
Ladies, I didn't wanna run off without saying hello.
我们好像有点赶时间
Seem to be in a big rush around here.
俄国人绝对没有放慢脚步
The Russians certainly aren't slowing down any.
做不出冰箱的
They can't build a damn refrigerator.
人怎么会先上太空？
How the heck did they beat us into space?
你们在太空总署的工作是什么？
And what do you ladies do for NASA?
计算你们发射与着陆的轨道
Calculate your trajectories. Launch and landing.
没有数字就寸步难行
You can't get anywhere without the numbers.
-是的
No, sir.
格伦先生，工程部的玛莉杰克森
Mary Jackson, Mr. Glenn. Engineering.
能和你共事让我引以为豪
And I'm proud as the devil to be working with you.
谢谢，玛莉
Thank you, Mary.
约翰
John.
我们进去吧    -是，先生
John, let's take it inside. Yes, sir.
各位    -很高兴认识你们
Guys. Nice meeting you guys.
谢谢你，上校    -祝您好运
Thank you, Colonel. Good luck, sir.
上帝保佑各位
God bless you all.
谢谢，真是太好了
Thank you. That's wonderful.
谢谢你们
Thank you!
“有色人种专用”
哈里逊先生要你确认
Mr. Harrison wants you to confirm
红石火箭测试的发射与着陆
launch and landing for the Redstone rocket test.
我不能验算看不到的数据
I cannot work on what I cannot see, Mr. Stafford.
我做不到
It's illegible.
这部门已经有…
Those numbers have already been confirmed
两个工程师和我确认过数字
by two engineers in this department and myself.
这只是形式上的检查
This is more or less a dummy check.
“擎天神火箭座舱压力”
“红石火箭轨道表”
这一个门，我们要两倍大，好吗？
You have one, we make it two. Make it double, okay?
非这样不可，一定要弄
We gotta get it. Just make it happen.
没人想到要先量好尺寸？
No one thought to measure these things?
恐怕没有，先生
I'm afraid not, sir.
你要我们停下来吗？
Well, would you like us to stop?
不，就…
No. No, just...
就继续下去吧
Actually, no. Just keep going.
事实上，用大榔头吧
In fact, use the big hammer.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
听到了没，去拿大榔头
Come on, use the big hammer. You heard the man. Let's go.
小心
Watch out.
“东侧计算室”
女士
Ma'am.
递送员可以去拿你算好的资料
Our runner can pick up your work, Dorothy.
你应该坐着工作，不该走来走去
You need to be working, not walking.
现在是休息时间，没有问题
Oh, it's break time, ma'am. No trouble at all.
既然你都来了
Since you made the trip...
可以把这批资料带回去
you can take that batch over there.
当然，米契尔女士
Sure thing, Mrs. Mitchell.
你还要什么吗？ 是，女士
You need something else? Yes, ma'am.
你知道技术部那边
I was wondering if you know what they're building
在盖什么吗？
over in the tech wing.
叫IBM的东西
It's called an IBM.
大型主机
A mainframe machine.
那个东西能马上算出
Apparently, it can do our calculations
我们做的计算
in a fraction of the time.
对太空总署应该很有用
I guess that's good for NASA.
你快走吧，最好一趟就拿完
Hurry on, now. Best if you do it in one trip.
借过
Excuse me.
“擎天神  轨道”
“红石  失败”
你好
Hi.
“有色人种女用洗手间”
你在看什么，保罗？
What are you looking at, Paul?
那个正确吗？
Is that correct?
对
Yeah.
那是谁算的？
Whose work is that?
我说，那是谁算的？
I said, whose work is that?
凯萨琳哥柏，长官
Katherine Goble, sir.
你好    -你好
Hello. Hi.
你怎么知道
How did you know the Redstone
红石撑不了轨道飞行？
couldn't support orbital flight?
那是机密资讯
That's classified information.
是最高机密
It's top secret.
红石测试一直失败不是机密
It's no secret why the Redstone tests keep failing.
次轨道太空飞行没问题
It's fine for sub-orbital flight
但是它撑不了座舱的的重量
but it can't handle the weight of the capsule
无法推进到太空里
and push it into space.
数字不会骗人
Numbers don't lie.
你靠这些就算出来了？
And you figured all that out with this?
有一半的数据被拿掉了
Half the data is redacted.
观察字里行间就能看出端倪
But what's there tells a story if you read between the lines.
我们知道发射地到轨道间的距离
The distance from launch to orbit, we know.
知道红石火箭
Redstone mass, we know.
和水星座舱的重量
Mercury capsule weight, we know.
数据里有飞行速度
And the speeds are there in the data.
你算出来了
You did the math.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
我跳脱眼前的数字
I looked beyond.
你怎么知道擎天神火箭？
How do you know about the Atlas rocket?
那不是数学
That's not math.
那项资料不在这里
That data is not here.
那确实是机密
Like you said, it's classified.
我对着光看
I held it up to the light.
你对着光看？
You held it up to the light?
是，长官
Yes, sir.
喔，我看到了
Well, there it is.
对
Mmm-hmm.
擎天神
Atlas.
你叫什么名字？
What's your name?
凯萨琳哥柏
Katherine Goble.
你是间谍吗，凯萨琳？
Are you a spy, Katherine?
你说什么？
Am I what?
你是俄国间谍吗？
I said, are you a Russian spy?
不，长官
No, sir.
我不是俄国人
I'm not Russian.
她不是俄国人，长官
She's not Russian, sir.
那好，我们没什么可损失
All right then, we have nothing to lose here.
给她所有资讯
Give her everything she needs
计算薛帕的轨道
to work on Shepard's trajectories.
不要修改资料，清楚吗？
Without redaction. Are we clear on that?
你确定要这样吗？
Are we sure about this?
有什么问题吗，保罗？
What's the issue, Paul?
你听到她说的了
You heard her.
她不是间谍
She's not a spy.
我觉得这样不好
I just don't think it's a good idea.
你知道什么才好吗？更深色的墨水
You know what I think's a good idea? Darker ink.
我觉得更深的墨水比较好
I think darker ink's a good idea.
茹丝，把资料给她
Ruth, could you pass it along?
-是
Yes, sir.
谢谢你，凯萨琳
Thank you, Katherine.
谢谢您，长官
Thank you, sir.
审问结束了
This interrogation's over.
“限有色人种入内”
你的功劳都能让他们来回月球了
You can probably get to the moon and back with this.
但我还是不能用洗手间
Just not the bathroom.
至少他们没对你做的视而不见
At least they're not blind of what you do.
我们很快就不重要了
It's not gonna matter soon.
IBM会取代我们的工作
This IBM's gonna put us all out of work.
你好吗？    -我们该怎么办？
How you doing? What can we do about it?
只有一个方法
Only one thing to do.
尽量学习，让我们有价值
Learn all we can, make ourselves valuable.
不论如何，NSomewhere down the line, a human being
按下按钮的还是人类\
is gonna have to push the buttons.
没错
That's right.
“限有色人种入内”
我的天
Oh, mercy.
她一定是迷路了
Well, she must be lost.
女性不能参加
NASA doesn't commission females
工程师训练计划
for the Engineer Training Program.
符合资格的人就能申请那个职位
That position is available to any qualified applicant.
对，但是你不符合学历要求
Right. Except, you don't have the educational requirements.
我有
I have a bachelor's degree
数学和物理学学士学位
in mathematics and physical science.
和这里的大多数的工程师一样
It's the same as most engineers around here.
现在需要维吉尼亚大学
We now require advanced extension courses
进修课程学历
through the University of Virginia.
员工手册附录里有写
It's in the employee handbook. In addendum.
“太空总署员工手册”
你大概没看吧
In case you haven't read it.
每次有机会往前进
Every time we have a chance to get ahead...
他们就把终点线往后移
they move the finish line.
我只是照规定做事
I just follow the rules around here.
我也希望我所有下属
And I expect everyone who works for me
照规定来
to follow them as well.
没有人有特殊待遇
There are no special circumstances for anyone.
你们有工作就应该感恩了
Y'all should be thankful you have jobs at all.
“不能前往维吉尼亚大学上课者”
"For those that cannot attend classes at the University of Virginia...
“可选择进修课程”
"advanced extension courses are available
“开课地点为汉普顿高中”
"at the Hampton High School."
那里还是种族隔离学校，玛莉
That's still a segregated school, Mary.
尽管违宪，这里还是有种族隔离
Virginia acts like Brown versus Board of Education
本不该发生
never happened.
他们绝对不会让黑人女性
They are never gonna allow a colored woman
在全白人的学校上课
to just take classes at an all-white school.
听起来没错
Well, sounds about right.
你只会说这个吗？
That's all you gonna say?
我才不想听你
I'm not gonna sit here all day and listen to you complain
整天抱怨
about the way things are.
我们在玩牌
We're trying to play cards.
去法院请愿，争取你要的
Petition the court. Fight for what you want.
但不要光说不练
But quit talking about it.
我在抱怨吗？    -好几天了
I've been complaining? For days.
各位女士
Ladies.
不准再讲工作的事了
Not one more peep about work.
算我一份
Deal me in.
凯萨琳？
Katherine?
来吧    -糟了
- Come on. - Oh, no.
过来    -你来
Right here. You.
孩子，我就需要这个
Child, I needed this.
谢谢你
Thank you.
不要再让她喝了，凯萨琳
Don't give her anymore, Katherine.
不会了，因为她喝完了
I can't. She drank it all.
听着，我没事
Listen, I'm fine.
我完全没有问题
I'm as fine as I have ever been.
你完全喝醉了
You're drunk as you've ever been.
我们来跳舞啦，姊妹们
Come on. Let's dance, ladies.
来嘛，小凯，来跳舞
Come on, Kat. Let's dance.
去和她跳舞，凯萨琳
Go and dance with her, Katherine.
快点，去玩啊
Come on. Get out here.
把它藏起来
Hide that.
我们教你跳舞
We gonna teach you how to dance.
-你跳吧
You go ahead.
就这样    -音乐太小声了
All right. It's too low.
我们要教你怎么追男人    -这就对了
We gonna teach you how to get a man.
教我？你说什么？    -快点
- Teach me? What? - That's right. Come on!
你要知道怎么跳舞
You got to know how to dance.
慢，慢    -就这样
Slow. Slow. Come on.
转一圈    -转、转
Twirl it around. Twirl, twirl.
对了    -转、转、转
Yes! Twirl, twirl, twirl.
看看她，桃乐斯
Whoo! Look at her, Dorothy.
这样能在那些舞蹈比赛中获胜吗？
Can I win me one of those fancy dance contests?
转一圈
Whip it around.
然后在外面啊
Yeah, and on the outside.
比妈妈的还好吗？
Was it better than Mama's?
其实没有
No, not really.
结束种族隔离
Segregation must go!
结束种族隔离  结束种族隔离
结束种族隔离
Segregation must go!
“60年代的领袖，尼克森总统”
不要看那些
Don't pay attention to all that.
我们不要惹麻烦
We're not part of that trouble. Go on.
“总统选甘迺迪”
“限有色人种入内”
“限白人入内”
“注意，他们必定…”
"Mind. They must have done..."
我们不想惹麻烦
We don't want any trouble in here.
我不是来找麻烦的，女士
Oh, I'm not here for any trouble, ma'am.
你们在这里干嘛？
What are you here for?
来找书
A book.
有色人种区也有书
You have books in the colored section.
但没有我要找的书
It doesn't have what I'm looking for.
那也没办法
That's just the way it is.
走吧，你们很清楚规定
“汉普顿公立图书馆”
Go on, now. You know better than this.
手拿开，不要碰我儿子
Get your hands off my boys! Don't touch them.
希望你今天愉快
You have a blessed day.
隔离与平等是两件事
Separate and equal are two different things.
现在的情况不代表就是对的
Just 'cause it's the way, doesn't make it right.
懂吗？
Understand?
知道了，妈妈
Yes, Mama.
你们的行为正确，就没有错
You act right, you are right.
这是一定的
That's for certain.
懂吗？
Understand?
知道了，妈妈
Yes, Mama.
你拿了那本书，妈妈？
You took that book, Mama?
儿子，我有缴税
Son, I pay taxes.
图书馆里的一切都是用税买的
And taxes pay for everything in that library.
你有付钱就不叫“拿”
Can't take something you already paid for.
“福传是令人期待的新语言”
"Fortran is a new and exciting language...
“是程式设计师与电脑沟通的语言”
"used by programmers to communicate with computers.
“令人兴奋，是未来的浪潮”
"It is exciting, as it is the wave of the future."
好，笑一个
All right, everybody smile.
大家都要笑
- Everybody smile. - Aw!
许愿    -许愿
Make a wish. Make a wish.
吹蜡烛，再一次
Blow. Try again.
很棒
There you go.
里奥德，你该找工作了
Leonard, you need to get you a job now.
两份工作
Two jobs.
你的小孩九岁了，你什么打算？
Your baby is nine. What are you gonna do?
谢谢，你来得正是时候
Thank you, man. Yeah, you're just in time.
看看谁来了
Look at that.
谁？    -真是惊喜
Look at what? What a surprise.
没什么好抱怨的
Can't complain, man.
最好是惊喜
I'll say.
一定是霍华邀请他的    -对
Howard must have invited him. Mmm-hmm.
我去帮忙弄花
Let me go help them with those flowers.
华特，你乖一点
Walter, you behave yourself.
你知道，我…    -对
Now, you know, I'm just... Yeah.
宝贝就是这样，扭一扭
That's right, baby. Shake it.
对，就是这样
Yeah. There you go.
很高兴见到你    -谢谢
Good to see you. Yes. Thank you.
我应该向你道歉
I believe I owe you an apology.
刚刚算吗？
Well, was that it?
能让我在跳舞时道歉吗？
Can I make it while we dance?
我那天好像说错话了，哥柏女士
I'm afraid I simply misspoke the other day, Mrs. Goble.
我离开有一阵子了
I've been away for a long time.
我想我有点脱节了
I imagine I'm just out of practice.
嗯
Mmm-hmm.
我希望你再给我一次机会
I was hoping you'd allow me to start over.
嗯
Mmm-hmm.
老实说
See, the thing is...
我想多认识你一些
I have an interest in getting to know you better.
嗯
Mmm-hmm.
你很难取悦
You're one tough customer, huh?
你还没说对不起
You haven't said you're sorry yet.
也是
Right.
没错
Of course.
对不起，凯萨琳
I'm sorry, Katherine.
为什么，吉姆？
For what, Jim?
我小看你了
Underestimating you.
小看了像你这样的女性
And any other woman like you...
但我想能和你并驾齐驱的也不多
Though I don't imagine there's many.
这样才算正式的道歉
That's good practice, right there.
音乐暂停播出
We interrupt this musical programming
新闻快报
with breaking news.
苏联新闻单位宣布
The Soviet news agency has announced
俄国太空人尤里加加林
that Russian cosmonaut, Yuri Gagarin,
成为首位…
has become the first man in space.
在太空
Gagarin completed
完成绕行地球轨道的人
one full orbit around the planet
耗时108分钟
in 108 minutes.
继续收听本台随时提供的
Stay tuned to this station for more details
最新消息
as they become available.
看来我们被抛在后头了
Guess that puts us behind the curve.
东方号火箭
The Vostok-1 rocket...
将俄国太空人加加林的3KA座舱…
delivered Russian cosmonaut Yuri Gagarin's 3KA capsule...
“首位进入太空的人类：加加林”
于世界标准时间6点07分进入轨道
into orbit, at 6:07 UTC...
7点55分重新进入俄国领空
Reentering Russian airspace at 7: 55 UTC.
证明人类
Proving conclusively that man
能在轨道太空飞行中生存
could survive orbital space flight.
加加林获颁
Gagarin was awarded
列宁勋章与金星…
the Order of Lenin and a Gold Star...
我们输得一败涂地
Well, they beat the pants off us.
走吧
Let's go.
并获得…
He is also conferred the title...
-去搞清楚怎么飞到太空
Let's learn how to fly to space.
苏联第一太空人头衔
"First Soviet Astronaut"...
被尊称为国家英雄
and has been proclaimed a national hero.
这是前所未有的胜利之日
This is a day of unprecedented triumph...
俄国太空计划
for the Russian space program
在太空竞赛中
and a crushing blow for America
痛击美国
in the race for space.
谢谢各位留下来
I wanna thank everyone for staying.
我知道很晚了，看到那些…
I know it's late. And after what I just saw,
我相信大家都急着想回家
I'm sure everyone's probably anxious to just go home.
在回去前，我要问一个问题
Before we do, I just have to ask a question.
也是我一直问自己
The same one
的一个问题
I've been asking myself all the way over here...
也就是…
which is...
我们怎么会在两人赛中
How the hell did we find ourself
拿第二名？
in second place in a two-man race?
有人能回答我吗？
Anybody?
保罗？
Paul?
我想格伦说得对
And I think Glenn said it pretty well.
他们比我们努力
They're just outworking us.
我必须这么想，因为…
The reason I have to think that
我拒绝相信
is because I refuse to believe
俄国人比我们聪明
that the Russians are smarter than us
或是他们比较进步
or that they have more technology,
比较认真
or that they care more.
但我不知道，这可能吗？
But I don't know. Is that possible?
有没有可能？
Is it possible that it actually
他们就是比较在乎
means more to them?
我们现在处于危及存亡之秋
We're in the fight of our lives, people.
不是什么轻松愉快之旅
We're not on some epic joy ride.
有七张脸孔
I just saw seven faces
露出不信任我们的表情
who aren't sure that we can get there.
这是我们的问题
This is our problem.
所以现在…
And so as of right now
你们只需要记住两件事
there's only two things you need to know going forward.
一，留下来加班
One is staying here, working late,
就是你们的人生
that's gonna be a fact of life.
二，不要妄想你们
And two, don't expect your paychecks
会领到加班费
to reflect the extra time it's gonna take
为了赢过那些混蛋，加班是应该的
to catch up and pass those bastards.
至于不能接受的人
For those of you who can't work that way,
我也了解，谢谢你们之前的付出
I understand and thank you for what you've done.
而其他人…
For everyone else...
我建议你们打电话回家
I suggest you call your wives
向妻子说明情况
and tell them how it's gonna be.
我先开始
I'll start with mine.
“红石无人操纵火箭测试”
山姆，调高一点
Sam, turn it up. Turn it up.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
约翰    -早安，长官
John. Morning, sir.
7-5，7-4，7-3
7-5, 7-4, 7-3...
下班前算好
End of the day.
好，看起来可以
Okay, we're looking good.
好  好
Okay.
“IBM 7090资料处理系统”
长官，可能是选择锁
Sir, might be the selector latch.
-我去走走
I'm taking a walk.
我们以服务国家为荣
We're honored to serve our country.
我们不担心危险
So we don't think about danger.
我们没有时间害怕
We don't have time to be scared.
我们要完成工作
We got a job to do.
早安    -早安
Good morning. Good morning.
“有色人种入口”
杰克森女士
Mrs. Jackson.
“收件”
有色人种的座位在法院后方
Colored seats are at the back of the court room.
谢谢你，女士
Thank you, ma'am.
你们谁想先去？
So, which one of you wants to go first?
“福传语言”
“垂直面，水平面”
IBM 7090资料处理系统
The IBM 7090 data processing system.
它有能力计算…
It has the capability of solving
超过24,000笔的乘法
over 24,000 multiplications
而且只要一秒
per second.
我的天，那快得像闪电一样
Holy Moses, that's lightning fast.
他们弄不好那个系统的
They'll never get that to work.
最后还是会成功的
Oh, it'll run eventually.
到时候我们必须知道怎么写程式
And when it does, we have to know how to program it.
除非你们想丢了工作
Unless you'd rather be out of a job.
不，女士
No, ma'am.
兹林先生…
Mr. Z...
我拿到法院请愿日期了
I got a court date.
“电脑使用
"The computer uses it
高速储存单位…”
"as its high speed storage unit,
“做为资讯保存装置”
"an information holding device."
你有大脑啊
You have a brain.
这我可以应付
That I can work with.
这个位置不对
This is in the wrong spot.
好女孩
Attagirl.
茹丝
Ruth.
是，长官    -联络卡纳维尔角基地
Yes, sir. Get me the Cape on the line.
薛帕的轨道要更新
Shepard's trajectories need to be updated.
搞什么
Wow.
她在哪里？
Where is she?
♪ You and I are no different from each other
♪ Shut our eyes when we slumber I see numbers
♪ Black and white we're computers, I am color
♪ Don't act like you was there when you wasn't
♪ I don't want no free ride
♪ Some nights I cry
♪ 'Cause I can see the day comin'
♪ Together we fly
♪ Oh, but no more runnin'
♪ No more runnin'
你跑到哪里去了？
Where the hell have you been?
我到处找你，你却不在位子上
Everywhere I look, you're not where I need you to be.
不是我的错觉
It's not my imagination.
你每天到底混到哪里去了？
Now where the hell do you go every day?
去洗手间，长官
To the bathroom, sir.
去洗手间？
To the bathroom?
去该死的洗手间
To the damn bathroom.
一天去40分钟？
For 40 minutes a day?
你在洗手间干嘛？
What do you do in there?
我们时间紧迫，我这么信任你
We're T-minus zero here. I put a lot of faith in you.
这里没有我的洗手间
There's no bathroom for me here.
什么叫“没有你的洗手间”？
What do you mean there is no bathroom for you here?
这里没有洗手间
There is no bathroom.
这栋楼没有有色人种洗手间
There are no colored bathrooms in this building
只有西侧大楼有
or any building outside the West Campus,
距离这里800公尺
which is half a mile away.
你知道这件事吗？
Did you know that?
我要走到非洲才能上厕所
I have to walk to Timbuktu just to relieve myself.
而且我也不能使用脚踏车
And I can't use one of the handy bikes.
你可以想像一下，哈里逊先生
Picture that, Mr. Harrison.
我的制服
My uniform...
过膝裙，高跟鞋
Skirt below my knees, my heels,
简单的珍珠项链
and a simple string of pearls.
喔，我没有珍珠
Well, I don't own pearls.
因为有色人种拿的薪水
Lord knows you don't pay coloreds enough
买不起珍珠
to afford pearls!
我没日没夜工作得像条狗
And I work like a dog, day and night,
只靠你们不屑碰的
living off of coffee from a pot
那壶咖啡过日子
none of you wanna touch!
所以，不好意思
So, excuse me
我一天必须
if I have to go to the restroom
要去几次洗手间
a few times a day.
“有色人种专用”
“有色人种女用洗手间”
你们看到了
There you have it.
再也没有有色人种洗手间
No more colored restrooms.
没有白人洗手间
No more white restrooms.
就是简单的马桶而已
Just plain old toilets.
随便你想去哪里的厕所都行
Go wherever you damn well please.
最好是离你的座位近一点的
Preferably closer to your desk.
在太空总署尿尿不用分肤色
Here at NASA, we all pee the same color.
听说你感冒了
Heard you was fighting the flu.
我带了一些汤过来
Figured you could use some soup.
女孩们可以吃点热的
Hot meal for the girls.
进来吧
Come on in.
不好意思
Excuse me.
女孩们，我们来祷告
Okay, ladies. Let's say grace.
低下头
Bow your heads.
主啊，感谢祢赐我们这餐
Dear Lord, thank you for this meal.
请庇佑食物
We ask that you bless this food
使其庇佑我们的身体
so that it may bless our bodies.
以耶稣之名祷告
In Jesus's name we pray.
阿们    -阿们
Amen. Amen.
“1961年5月5日”
“艾伦薛帕的火箭发射”
在卡纳维尔角是历史性的一天
It's a historic day, here at Cape Canaveral.
我们引颈期盼的是…
And here's what we can expect.
艾伦薛帕的自由7号将进入太空
Alan Shepard and Freedom 7 will be launched into space
时速大约187公里
at an altitude of about 116 miles an hour.
桃乐斯快来啊    -我的天，快点
Dorothy, come on, you gonna miss it! Oh, boy! Go.
快点，桃乐斯    -我来了
- Come on, Dorothy. - I'm coming.
他会在佛州
...then he will land around 35 miles
离岸56公里处降落
off the coast of Florida...
接他回来的…
where he'll be picked up
是尚普兰湖号航母
by the men of the USS Lake Champlain...
-你总算来了
Finally. Come over here.
这是航母历史性的任务
who set out for this historic purpose.
自由7号，液态氧槽…
Freedom 7, we're going to have to bleed off
现在要泄压
some of the pressure inside the liquid oxygen tank.
应该能降低舱内温度，结束
“自由7号”
That should reduce the temperature inside the capsule. Over.
快啊，座舱指挥中心
Any day now, CAPCOM.
把问题搞定，点燃引信吧
Fix your little problem and light this candle.
收到，自由7号
Roger that, Freedom 7.
准备
Stand by.
温度恢复正常了
Temperature is returning to normal.
再做一次发射状态检查
Running one more launch status check.
所有系统准备完成
All systems now go.
进入最后倒数阶段
Move to final countdown sequence.
Moving to final countdown sequence.
收到
Roger that.
倒数读秒，10
We're at T-minus 10...
nine...
eight...
seven...
six...
five...
four...
three...
two...
one...
zero.
已经点燃
We have ignition.
升空了
And we have lift off.
上去吧
Get up there.
升空，开始计时
Lift off, and the clock is started.
燃料系统开，2.5G
Fuel is go. 2.5G.
快上去吧
Get on up there.
撑住
- Come on! - Lift off at
-距离升空后34分钟
34 minutes after the hour.
倾斜88度，轨道良好
Pitch 88. Trajectory is good.
偏航没问题
Yaw is okay.
切换到手动操作
Switching manual roll.
好
Yes!
在全世界面前
For the eyes of the world
我们看见太空
now look into space,
看见月球与周围的星球
to the Moon and to the planets beyond.
太好了    -我们成功了
Yes! We did it!
我们发誓
And we have vowed...
我们不会任由敌国
that we shall not see it governed...
竖立征服主宰的旗帜
by a hostile flag of conquest...
而是以自由和平的风帆…
but by a banner of freedom and peace.
在这片新的海洋上带领我们
We set sail on this new sea...
因为我们将获得新的知识
because there is new knowledge to be gained...
获得新的权利
and new rights to be won.
我们选择在这十年内登陆月球
We choose to go to the Moon in this decade
并完成其他的事
and do the other things...
不是因为这些事很容易
not because they are easy...
而是因为它们很困难
but because they are hard.
帮我们保住了工作
for the continued job security.
古斯葛利森是下一个
Uh, Gus Grissom's up next.
他也要搭红石火箭进行次轨道飞行
Another suborbital flight with a Redstone.
这是格伦搭擎天神号前的
It's our last shot
最后机会
before we strap Glenn to the Atlas
老天保佑我们能让他回来
and pray we can bring him back down.
对，我猜他会
Yes, and I imagine he'd like us
希望我们先算好数学
to have the math worked out beforehand.
做得好，各位
Good work, gentlemen.
回去陪小孩吃饭吧
Go have dinner with your kids
然后再回来工作
and let's get back to work.
♪ Look what you've done to me
♪ Make me behave like I wouldn't ever
♪ I know you're the one for me
♪ Your essence is the ink in the word "forever"
我想这是亲你的好时机
I think it's high time that I kissed you, Katherine.
为什么？
Oh, and why is that?
我想你也喜欢我，像我喜欢你一样
Figured you attracted to me, same as I to you.
是吗？    -对
Is that right? Mmm-hmm.
不然你早就要我回家了
Or you would have told me to get going a long time ago.
我很久没和男人接吻了
Haven't kissed a man in a long time.
几乎快忘记怎么做了
Almost forgot how to.
FBI逮捕涉嫌
The FBI has arrested four white men
在阿拉巴马州…
accused of throwing a fire bomb
攻击黑人解放团体巴士
into a Freedom Rider bus
的四名白人
outside of Anniston, Alabama...
宝贝    -巴士里很快…
- Hi, babies. - The bus filled rapidly
妈妈    -弥漫黑烟
Hi, Mama. ...with black smoke.
我们都趴在地上
We all hit the floor.
所有人都发现巴士着火了
All of us realized the bus was on fire...
必须逃出去才行
and had to go out into the mob.
小孩不需要看这些
The kids don't need to be watching this.
-他们需要看
They need to see this.
我们在伯明罕逃出巴士后
When we got off the bus in Birmingham...
每个人都该看
Everybody needs to see this.
有人硬把我拉出门
...took me and forced me out of the door...
然后被丢进人群里
and threw me into the crowd.
后来有个大家伙和几个人一起揍我
And then I was beaten by one big guy and several others.
我们认为自己是为国家奉献
We think we're rendering a great service to our nation.
这不只是为了我们而奋斗
For this is not a struggle for ourselves alone.
是为了拯救美国的灵魂而奋斗
It is a struggle to save the soul of America.
玛莉杰克森
Mary Jackson.
请愿前往汉普顿高中修课
Petition to attend courses at Hampton High School.
早安，庭上
Good morning, Your Honor.
汉普顿高中是白人学校，女士
Hampton High School is a white school, Mrs. Jackson.
是的，庭上，我了解
Yes, Your Honor. I'm aware of that.
维吉尼亚州还是实施种族隔离
Virginia, still a segregated state.
不管联邦政府怎么说
Regardless of what the federal government says,
不管最高法院怎么说
regardless of what the Supreme Court says,
我们的法律才是法律
our law is the law.
庭上，请容我说句话
Your Honor, if I may.
我相信有些特殊情况
I believe there are special circumstances
可以考虑
to be considered.
有什么能让黑人女性
What would warrant a colored woman
念白人学校？
attending a white school?
我能上前吗，庭上？
May I approach your bench, sir?
庭上
Your Honor...
您应该最能了解首开先例
you of all people should understand
的重要性
the importance of being first.
怎么说，杰克森女士？
How's that, Mrs. Jackson?
您是家族中
You were the first in your family
最早加入美军的成员
to serve in the Armed Forces.
美国海军
U.S. Navy.
最早念大学的家族成员
The first to attend university.
乔治梅森大学
George Mason.
也是最早连任的州法官
And the first state judge to be recommissioned
连续三位州长都任命您
by three consecutive governors.
你有做功课
You've done some research.
是的，庭上
Yes, sir.
你的重点是什么？
What's the point?
重点是，庭上
The point is, Your Honor...
维吉尼亚州从未有黑人女性
no Negro woman in the state of Virginia...
曾经到全白人学校念过书
has ever attended an all-white high school.
这是前所未闻的事
It's unheard of.
是的，前所未闻
Yeah. Unheard of.
在艾伦薛帕坐在火箭上之前
And before Alan Shepard sat on top of a rocket,
没有美国人曾经到过太空
no other American had ever touched space.
现在，他将永远被世人记住
And now, he will forever be remembered
这个出身新罕布夏州的美国海军
as the U.S. Navy man from New Hampshire,
是第一个进入星空的人
the first to touch the stars.
而我，庭上
And I, sir...
我要成为太空总署的工程师
I plan on being an engineer at NASA,
但没有修白人学校的课程
but I can't do that without taking them classes
我就做不到这件事
at that all-white high school.
我不能改变我的肤色
And I can't change the color of my skin.
所以我不得不选择做先锋
So I have no choice but to be the first.
但没有您，我无法成功
Which I can't do without you, sir.
庭上
Your Honor...
您今天将听见各种案件
out of all the cases you're gonna hear today...
100年后，哪一个案子是重要的？
which one is gonna matter 100 years from now?
哪一个案子能让您首开先例？
Which one is gonna make you the first?
只能上夜校
Only the night classes...
杰克森女士
Mrs. Jackson.
太好了
Yes, yes, yes!
Yes!
我的天，我不敢相信
Oh, my God. I cannot believe.
“葛利森发射着陆计划  作者…”
“保罗史塔佛与凯萨琳哥柏”
他说他会迟到多久？    -抱歉
How late did he say he was gonna be?
最多五分钟
Excuse me. No more than five minutes, sir.
古斯葛利森的座标
Gus Grissom's coordinates.
我想先算约翰格伦的轨道
Uh, I'd like to get a jump on John Glenn's trajectory.
你知道自己在说什么吗？
Do you have any idea what you're asking?
擎天神火箭的轨道发射需要时间
An orbital launch with an Atlas rocket is going to take time.
有什么问题吗？
Is there a problem?
哈里逊先生
Mr. Harrison...
我在想…
I was wondering.
我这辈子都在想
Uh-huh. I've been wondering my whole life,
你就说吧
so you just spit it out.
长官
Well, sir...
我想先算约翰格伦的轨道
I would like to get a jump on John Glenn's trajectory.
这不是加加减减
This isn't about plugging in numbers,
是要发明数学
it's about inventing the math.
我们讨论过了
And I think you and I talked about that, right?
那种数学不存在
It doesn't exist.
我做得到，长官
I can do it, sir.
你知道这些计算
Do you have any idea how exacting
要多精准吗？
these calculations have to be?
像从300公尺外发射短型霰弹枪
It's like shooting a sawed-off shotgun from a thousand feet
子弹还要通过小得看不见的洞一样
and getting that one BB through a hole so tiny, you can't even see it.
我看看
Okay, let me see what you've got.
-我的枪法很准，长官
I'm an excellent shot, sir.
葛利森的数字怎么样？
How have the Grissom numbers been?
完全正确
They've been spot on.
试算格伦的轨道吧
Give Glenn's orbit a go.
但要和史塔佛确认，懂吗？
But you run it all through Stafford, you understand?
是，长官
Yes, sir.
谢谢您
Thank you.
计算人员不能列为作者
Computers don't author reports.
座舱指挥中心，这里是自由钟7号
CAPCOM, this is Liberty Bell 7.
“1961年7月21日”
“收回古斯葛利森”
很清楚
Loud and clear.
好，到现在为止都很好
Okay, it's a nice ride up to now.
收到
Roger.
自由钟7号，杭特1号
Liberty Bell 7, this is Hook 1 approaching.
准备伸勾回收
Ready to hook on. Over.
自由钟7号听见了，结束
I read you loud and clear. Over.
舱口盖爆炸了，座舱指挥中心
The hatch is blown, CAPCOM.
自由钟7号座舱下沉
The Liberty Bell 7 capsule is taking on water.
古斯葛利森已经离开座舱
Gus Grissom is out of the capsule.
救援人员要把他从海水中
Rescuers are now going to pull him
拉出来
from the ocean waves.
可惜自由钟7号座舱无法回收
Unfortunately, the Liberty Bell 7 capsule is lost.
妈妈
Mama.
不行，我不行    -玛莉
I can't, I can't. Mary.
哈里逊先生
Mr. Harrison,
纳税人的钱和座舱…
taxpayer money sank into the ocean
一起沉到海底了
along with your capsule.
你怎么能确保约翰格伦
So what makes you think
安全回来？
you can bring John Glenn home safely?
先听我说
Let me say first...
发现的目的
discovery is never just for the sake
不是为了发现本身
of discovery, gentlemen...
而是为了人类的生存
but for the sake of human survival.
而且必然伴随着风险
And it will always come with a risk.
先成功的人就能制订规则
Whoever gets there first will make the rules.
所有文明都是如此
That's been true of every civilization.
所以，我认为各位
And so, I think the bigger question
更应该考虑的是
for this body to consider is...
你们希望谁在太空中发号施令？
who do you want calling the shots in space?
我们必须知道外面有什么，参议员
We have to know what's out there, Senator.
我们必须进入太空
We have to touch the stars,
才能保障生存
if only to ensure our own survival.
只有一个人能做到这件事
And only a man can do that.
我们会，也必须让格伦
We'll get John Glenn home safely
安全回来
because we have to.
因为他要告诉我们他看到什么
Because he has to tell us what he saw.
红石火箭直接往上飞
The Redstone rocket went straight up.
但座舱速度太慢
But the capsule didn't have enough speed
无法进入轨道
to go into orbit, so it came back down.
飞行路线是地球、次轨道、地球
Essentially a triangle. Earth, sub-orbit, Earth.
这是已知的计算方式
That math was known.
成功让薛帕、葛利森进入太空
That took Shepard, took Grissom.
但不适用于格伦
That cannot take Glenn.
那么擎天神火箭…
Now, the Atlas rocket...
能将我们推进轨道
that can push us into orbit.
向上升，让座舱进入椭圆轨道
Goes up, delivers the capsule into an elliptical orbit.
让地球的重力拉住它
Earth's gravity keeps pulling at it
但是速度够快所以不会撞上地球
but it's going so fast, it keeps missing the Earth.
所以才能停留在轨道上
That's how it stays in orbit.
至于让它回来…
Now, getting it back down...
是我们还不知道的计算
that's the math we don't know.
凯萨琳，请说
Yes, Katherine.
所以座舱会一直绕着地球
So the capsule will spin around the Earth forever
因为没有减速的力量？
because there's nothing to slow it down?
没错
That's right.
使它在正确的时刻慢下来
Slowing it down at precisely the right moment,
慢的程度也要恰到好处
at precisely the right amount,
就是我们要算的
that's the task.
凯萨琳，请说
Yes, Katherine.
所以它要从椭圆轨道…
So it needs to move from an elliptical orbit...
进入抛物线轨道
to a parabolic orbit.
对
Yes.
这就是返航关键点
That's the "Go/No-go."
完全没有犯错的空间
Now at this point, it's a pin head.
如果他太快掉回来…
We bring him in too soon...
重返大气层时会着火
He burns up on reentry.
没错
That's right.
如果回来得太慢…
We bring him in too late...
他会被地球的重力推走
he's pushed out of Earth's gravity.
任何改变，质量、重量、速度
And any changes to mass, weight, speed, time...
时间、距离、摩擦力、风吹草动
distance, friction, or a puff of wind...
都会改变返航关键点
would alter the "Go/No-go."
我们就要重新计算
And we start our calculations over.
对
Yes.
我们要能选择重返大气层的位置
So we need to be able to choose this reentry point.
这个返航关键点必须很精确
Now this "Go/No-go," this has to be exact.
山姆
Sam.
这些是目前红石座舱
These are the latest Redstone numbers
的最新数字
in current capsule data.
显然我们知道发射点
Obviously, we know the launch spot.
谢谢
Thanks.
国防部的简报
A Pentagon briefing should illuminate
会说明海军回收区
where the Navy needs the recovery zone.
然后我们再往回推算
Then we work backwards from there.
剩下就靠我们了，开始工作吧
And the rest is on us, so let's get to work.
史塔佛先生
Uh, Mr. Stafford.
什么事，凯萨琳？
What, Katherine?
如果让我参加简报
If I could attend the briefings,
对计划会更有用
I'd be more useful to the project.
国防部简报不对外开放
Pentagon briefings are closed door.
对，但如果我们
Yes, but if we don't have the information
不知道改变
of the changes...
就不能立刻跟上
we can't keep up.
我需要马上知道改变
I need those changes as they occur.
这不能出错
As you said, it's a pin head.
凯萨琳，我们的工作就是这样
Katherine, that's the job.
你要做
You asked for this assignment,
就用现有的资料算
so just calculate with what you have.
不然我们就找做得到的人来
Or we'll find someone who can.
好
Okay.
好女孩
Attagirl.
你在干嘛？你不能进来这里
What the hell are you doing? You can't be in here.
你是谁？
Who are you?
我是西侧计算组的
I'm with the West Computing Group.
我是桃乐斯范恩，先生
Dorothy Vaughan, sir.
这是很精密的设备
This is a very delicate piece of equipment.
抱歉，先生，我只是想帮忙
I'm sorry, sir. I'm just trying to be helpful.
最好是  比尔，数字出来了
Uh-huh. Bill, we've got numbers.
哪一种数字？
What kind of numbers?
真想不到
Well, I'll be.
你刚说你叫什么名字？
What's your name again?
桃乐斯范恩
Dorothy Vaughan.
“友谊7号发射预测”
长官，这是友谊7号的参数
Sir, the parameters for Friendship 7.
这些都还没确定
Oh, this is all moot.
我们要修改座舱的窗户
We're altering the window on the capsule.
什么时候改的？    -6分钟前
When did this happen? Six minutes ago.
数字改变了，重算
The math is changing. Start over.
长官，让我参加简报就能即时…
Sir, if I could attend the briefings, I could stay current...
凯萨琳，我们谈过这件事了
Katherine, we have been through this.
不可能
It is not possible.
没有女性与会的相关规定
There is no protocol for women attending.
也没有男性绕行地球的
There's no protocol for a man
相关规定
circling the Earth either, sir.
总之事情就是这样
Okay. That is just the way things are.
“友谊7号发射预测  作者…”
“保罗史塔佛与凯萨琳哥柏”
窗户变更后的
Colonel Glenn's launch coordinates,
格伦上校发射座标
accounting for the window change, sir.
我说过
I have told you this.
计算人员不能署名，重做
Computers don't author reports. Fix it.
那些是我算的，应该有我的名字
Those are my calculations. My name should be on it.
事情就不是这样的
That is not the way this works.
保罗，怎么回事？
Paul. What's happening here?
哈里逊先生，我想参加今天的简报
Mr. Harrison, I would like to attend today's briefing.
为什么？
And why is that?
数据改变得很快，座舱设计也会变
Sir, the data changes so fast. The capsule changes.
重量和着陆区
The weight and the landing zones
每天都在变
are all changing, every day.
你们开完会
I do my work, you attend these briefings,
本来算好的又要重算
I have to start over.
格伦上校还有几周就要升空了
Colonel Glenn launches in a few weeks.
我们还没算出正确的数字
We don't have the math figured out yet.
为什么她不能开会？
Why is it she can't attend?
因为她等级不够，艾尔
Because she doesn't have clearance, Al.
如果我不能尽快…
I cannot do my work effectively
拿到数据和资讯
if I do not have all of the data
工作就没有效率
and all of the information as soon as it's available.
我要一起开会，同步获得资讯
I need to be in that room, hearing what you hear.
平民不能参加
Pentagon briefings are not for civilians.
国防部机密简报
It requires the highest clearance.
我觉得
I feel like I'm the best person
我是说明计算的最佳人选
to present my calculations...
你不会放弃的吧？    -我不会
You're not gonna let this go, are you? No, I am not.
她是女人，没有相关规定…
And she is a woman. There is no protocol
让女性参加会议
for a woman attending these meetings.
-听到了，保罗
Okay, I get that part, Paul.
但是在这些墙后面…
But within these walls,
是谁制订规则？
who makes the rules?
是您，您才是长官
You, sir. You are the boss.
只是你得展现长官的魄力
You just have to act like one. Sir.
你要安静
You keep quiet.
谢谢您
Thank you.
早安
Good morning.
各位先生
Gentlemen.
这是轨道
This is Katherine Goble
与发射时机处的凯萨琳
with our Trajectory and Launch Window division.
她的工作和今天的内容相关
Her work is pertinent to today's proceedings.
过来
Come on.
给她张椅子吧？
Wanna get her a chair?
我们已经确认发射时机…
We have a confirmed launch window...
请给她椅子    -是，长官
Get her a chair, please. Yes, sir.
我们确认了友谊7号的
We have a confirmed launch window
发射时机
for Friendship 7.
现在讨论着陆区
Let's discuss a landing zone.
海军需要单一着陆区
The Navy needs a singular landing zone.
我们能回收的区域是52平方公里
20 miles square is what we can service for retrieval.
超出这个范围
Outside of that
座舱可能就无法回收
we risk the capsule's recovery.
我们希望有三个可能的回收点
We'd like three possible recovery areas.
我们不可能涵盖大半个海洋
We can't cover half the damn ocean.
无意冒犯
With all due respect,
但座舱设计每天都在变
our capsule's being altered daily.
现在绕行地球的速度是多少？
We're orbiting the Earth at what speed now?
火箭把座舱送到低轨道的速度…
17,544 miles per hour...
是每小时28,234公里
at the time the rocket delivers the capsule
进入低空间轨道
into low space orbit.
这张超速罚单可有得瞧了
Well, that's one hell of a speeding ticket.
好
Okay.
我们有飞行速度
So we have the vehicle's speed,
发射时机
the launch window...
现在讨论的着陆区
and for argument's sake, the landing zone
是巴哈马群岛
is the Bahamas.
这样可以算出返航关键点了吗？
Should be enough to figure the "Go/No-go"?
理论上来说可以
Yeah, in theory, sir.
现在不能只有理论了
We need to be past theory at this point.
我们用这些资讯就能算出
We'll be able to calculate a "Go/No-go"
返航关键点
with that information.
什么时候能算好？
When exactly is that gonna happen?
凯萨琳
Katherine.
开始算吧
Have a go at it.
可成功重新进入大气层的位置
The "Go" point for re-entry is 2,990 miles
距离格伦上校的着陆点4,812公里
from where we want Colonel Glenn to land.
假设着陆点在巴哈马群岛
If we assume that's the Bahamas...
时速28,234公里
at 17,544 miles per hour...
重新进入大气层
upon re-entry...
113公尺
370 feet...
倾斜角度是…
at a descent angle...
46.56度
of 46.56 degrees.
距离…
Distance...
速率的平方，正弦
velocity squared, sine...
重力的平方
gravity squared.
正弦，10公尺
Sine, 32 feet.
这样的距离是…
And the distance would be...
6,257,657公尺…
20,530,372 feet...
或4,812公里…
or 2,990 miles...
或46.33度
or 46.33 degrees.
好，着陆区
Okay, so that puts your landing zone
是北纬5.0667度
at 5.0667 degrees North...
西经77.3333度
77.3333 degrees West.
也就是这里
Which is here.
就在这里
Right here.
加减52平方公里
Give or take 20 square miles.
我喜欢她的数字
I like her numbers.
谢谢
Thank you.
前提是座舱
That, of course, is assuming
重返大气层的位置正确
the capsule hits the re-entry point exactly.
我们要怎么确定这一点？
How do we ensure that?
这部分我们还没算出来，各位
That's the math we don't have yet, gentlemen.
我们正在努力
We're working on it.
凯萨琳
Katherine.
这东西什么时候能发挥它的价值？
What's it gonna take to make this thing worth the price tag?
我们正在努力，哈里逊先生
We're just getting up to speed here, Mr. Harrison.
我需要更多人力
I need more manpower.
要程式设计师输入资讯卡
I need programmers, folks to feed the cards.
敲锣打鼓地去找
Get them, for crying out loud.
-好
Okay.
你是IBM的负责人对吗？    -是的
You're the IBM man, right? Yes, sir.
不择手段也要找到人
Go pull them out of the sky if you have to.
你要搞定，不然我就不付钱
Let's get ahead of this thing or I'm not paying you.
了解
Understood.
那个对了，那个也对
I got that one, I got that one.
你们全都拿不到薪水
I'm not paying any of you.
我？
Me?
对，是暂时的
Temporarily, yes.
我们需要IBM让格伦升空
We need the IBM for Glenn's launch.
主任工程师说
The lead engineer says you're good with the cards,
你会写程式卡之类的
programming and such.
那这边的女孩怎么办？
What about the girls here?
计算人员来不及算出
Human computers can't calculate an orbital flight
轨道飞行数字
in the time we have.
暂时会留在这里
They'll stay put for now.
以后呢？
What about after now?
格伦升空后
After Glenn's launch,
太空总署会解散计算组
NASA's dissolving the computing groups.
我不接受调职
I'm not accepting reassignment
除非她们跟着我
unless I bring my ladies with me.
你说什么？
Excuse me?
我们需要人力才能写程式
We're gonna need a lot of manpower to program that beast.
我一个人做不来
I can't do it alone.
这些女孩都准备好了，随时能上工
My gals are ready. They can do the work.
各位
Ladies.
我们调职了
We've been reassigned.
放下计算机
Leave your calculators.
新工作用不到它们了
You won't need them where we're going.
进入低空间轨道。“西侧计算组”
欢迎各位女士
Welcome, ladies.
知道你的工作是什么吗，保罗？
You know what your job is, Paul?
在人材中找到天才
Find the genius among those geniuses.
让我们成功
To pull us all up.
我们要不一起达到顶峰
We all get to the peak together
要不就全军覆没
or we don't get there at all.
是，晚安，长官
Yes. Well, good night, sir.
我不知道几点会到家
I don't know what time I'm coming home.
学校九点下课
Class ends at nine.
你有什么要说吗？
You got something to say?
我想你可能需要这个
I thought you might need these.
你可以装各种不同笔芯
You can refill them with any weight lead you want.
只要压上面这边
You see, you just hit the top like this.
然后笔芯会掉出来
All right? The lead comes out.
你再放新的进去
You put the new lead in...
就是新的笔了
and new pencil.
你会是一个好工程师的
You gonna make a fine engineer.
真的吗？
You think so?
真的
Yes.
没有人能阻挡玛莉杰克森
And nobody dare stand in the way...
实现她的梦想
of Mary Jackson's dreams.
连我也不能
Myself included.
别再惹我生气了
Don't make me mad again.
是的，夫人
Yes, ma'am.
也别害我迟到了
And don't make me late, either.
你会迟到，我要让你迟到
You gonna be late. I'mma make you late.
你不会迟到啦
You won't be late.
好，各位先生
All right, gentlemen.
今天要讲
Tonight, we discuss
普朗克爱因斯坦波长关系
Planck-Einstein wavelength relationships.
有事吗？
Yes?
我是玛莉杰克森
I'm Mary Jackson.
我注册入学了
I'm enrolled.
这门课
Well, the curriculum is not designed
没有对女性授课
for teaching a woman.
教学方式应该不分男女都一样
I imagine it's the same as teaching a man.
我没看到有色人种区
I don't see a colored section.
我可以随便坐吗？
Should I just take any seat?
谢谢
Thank you.
好
Okay. Uh...
普朗克-爱因斯坦
Planck-Einstein.
问题出在…
The problem...
座舱从椭圆轨道移
is when the capsule moves from an elliptical orbit
到抛物线轨道
to a parabolic orbit.
这里没有数学公式
There's no mathematical formula for that.
因为我们能计算发射与着陆
Because we can calculate launch and landing...
但没有轨道转换公式
but without this conversion
座舱就会留在轨道上，回不来地球
the capsule stays in orbit, we can't bring it back home.
也许我们根本想错了
Maybe we've been thinking about this all wrong.
怎么说？
How's that?
也许根本不需要新的算式
Maybe it's not new math at all.
可能是旧的算法
It could be old math.
用数字而不是理论
Something that looks at the problem numerically,
来思考
and not theoretically.
数学永远是最可靠的
Math is always dependable.
对你来说是这样
For you it is.
欧拉公式  欧拉公式
Euler's method.
对
Yes.
那超古老的    -但是有用
But that's ancient. But it works.
数学上行得通
It works numerically.
就是这个
That's it.
把它打出来
Let's type it up.
好
Okay.
“友谊7号发射着陆分析  史塔佛”
桃乐斯
Dorothy.
米契尔女士
Mrs. Mitchell.
你今天加班了
You're working late today.
好像总是这样
Seems to always happen that way.
对，好像是
Yes. Seems to.
谢谢
Thank you.
我听说IBM发挥全力了
I hear the IBM's up to full capacity.
你真的有能力使用它
You certainly have a knack for it.
我爸爸教过我一些机械的知识
My father taught me a thing or two about mechanics.
东侧组这边有几个女生
You know, I have a few girls in the East Group
也想学习相关知识
that have an interest in learning more about it.
这是未来趋势
It is the future.
如果你不介意，我可以带她们过去
I may bring them by, if it's all the same to you.
这不是我能决定的，女士
That's not my decision, ma'am.
主管才能决定
That would be the supervisor's.
你说的没错
Yes, that's true.
晚安，米契尔女士
Good night, Mrs. Mitchell.
听我说，桃乐斯
You know, Dorothy.
不管你怎么想…
Despite what you may think...
我对你们都没有偏见
I have nothing against y'all.
我知道
I know.
我知道你可能真的这么以为
I know you probably believe that.
晚安，凯萨琳
Good night, Katherine.
晚安
Good night.
妈妈    -宝贝
Mama! Hey, babies.
妈妈    -我回来了
Mama. Hi.
亲爱的
Hey.
我没有错过谁的生日吧
Oh, please don't tell me I missed someone's birthday.
没有啦
No, you didn't.
没有，妈妈
No, you didn't, Mama.
夫人，请坐
Madame, your seat.
谢谢你罗
Well, thank you.
今天是我的生日吗？
Wait, is it my birthday?
不是，妈妈
No, Mama.
你们都好漂亮
You all look so pretty.
妈妈，怎么回事？
Mama, what's going on?
晚安，凯萨琳
Good evening, Katherine.
你什么都不打算说吗？
So you're not gonna say anything?
我不是主角
It's not my place.
你们也不说？
You, either?
好吧，我才不要整晚…
Okay, I'm not gonna do this all night.
我的老天
Oh, mother of mercy.
这是给我的
That's for me.
你很伤心吗，妈妈？    -没有
Are you sad, Mama? No.
没关系，妈妈    -他是好人
It's okay, Mama. He's a good man.
我知道
I know.
我只是忍不住
I just can't help it.
他还没问你喔
He hasn't even asked you yet.
我知道，但他会的
I know, but he is.
你会吧？
You are, right?
如果你让我开口的话
If y'all will let me.
快点，她都在哭了
Well, go on. She's already crying.
安静
Oh, hush.
这是我妈妈的戒指
This was my mother's ring.
好美
It's beautiful.
她和我父亲结婚了…
She and my father were married for...
52年
For 52 years.
我想这是世界上最幸运的戒指了
Figure it's about as lucky a ring as you can get.
认识你那天，我打电话给我妈妈
The day I met you, I called my mother
说：“妈，我找到结婚的对象了”
and I said, "Mom, I met the woman I want to marry."
她说什么？
What'd she say?
她说：“她一定很不平凡”
She said, "She must be something, Jimmy.
真是的
"Really something."
那你说什么？
Then what'd you say?
我说：“不”
I said, "No.
“她不只不平凡”
"She's more than something.
“她胜过一切”
"She's everything."
现在…
Now...
我打算更浪漫的
I planned on this being more romantic.
我很快会补偿你
I'll make that up to you real soon.
没关系
It's okay.
但我知道娶了你…
But I know marrying you
也包括娶了你的女孩们
includes marrying your girls as well.
赞美上帝
Amen to that.
我愿意
I do.
我还没问你
I didn't ask you yet.
快点
Hurry up.
我的天哪
Oh, my goodness.
我的宝贝，你们看，很美是不是？
My babies. Look, girls, isn't it beautiful?
你看，妈妈
Look, Mama.
水星-擎天神太空船将使格伦…
The Mercury-Atlas space vehicle...
成为首位
which will put John Glenn,
进入地球轨道的美国人
the first American, into Earth's orbit...
目前已进行五次无人飞行测试
has already undergone five unmanned flight tests.
太空总署证实
NASA has confirmed
IBM 7090资料处理系统
that the IBM 790 data processing system...
已确认本次任务的…
has been utilized to confirm all of the mission 's...
发射与收回系统计算结果
launch and recovery system calculations.
调整与设备安装
The modifications and equipment installations
都符合进度
are progressing on schedule.
是，先生，就在这里
Yes, sir. Right in here.
您找我，长官？
You wanted to see me, sir?
坐下吧
Have a seat.
有什么问题吗，哈里逊先生？
Is there something wrong, Mr. Harrison?
不，没有问题
No, there's nothing wrong.
其实IBM计算的速度
In fact, our IBM is churning out numbers
超过任何人类
in fractions of the time any human can.
甚至比你还快
Present company included.
那是好事啊
That's good then.
也许吧
Maybe.
卡纳维尔角基地那边坚持
The thing is, the Cape's now insisting
要在那里进行所有后援准备
on doing all the backups down there, on site.
我懂
I see.
所以这里就不做后援了
So we won't be running backups here.
老实说，我们根本比不上IBM
And truth be told, we can't keep up with that IBM anyhow.
总之，这个部门
Long story short, we no longer need
不需要计算人员了
a computer in this department.
进步是一把双面刃
Progress is a double-edged sword.
你要回去西侧计算组了
Let's have you report back to the West Group for now.
我们会看看有没有其它职位
We'll see if we can find another assignment.
谢谢您，长官
Thank you, sir.
凯萨琳，我…
Katherine, I'm...
觉得很遗憾
I'm sorry about this.
这超出我的职权，希望你了解
It's out of my hands, if you can believe that.
我了解
I understand.
凯萨琳
Katherine.
我们听说你订婚了
We heard you got engaged.
是的
Yes.
你们真贴心
That's thoughtful of you.
好漂亮
They're lovely.
其实是哈里逊先生的主意
Mr. Harrison's idea, really.
但我想应该是他老婆挑的
Although I suspect his wife did the picking out.
他眼里除了数字应该没别的了
Can't imagine he has an eye for anything but numbers.
祝你婚礼顺利
Now you have a great wedding.
你在这里做得很好，凯萨琳
You did good work around here, Katherine.
你好，很高兴见到你
Hello there. Good to see you.
牧师，你好吗？    -你好吗？
Hi, Reverend. How you doing? How are you?
第一次我根本没什么感觉
I don't think I felt a thing the first time I did this.
我太紧张了
I was so nervous.
你跟那时候
You're just as beautiful
一样美丽
as you were back then.
你觉得吗？
- You think so? - Mmm.
只是老了一点
Just a little older.
还有胖了一点
And a little fuller.
但你很美
But you look good.
我们来吧，又一次
Well, here we go. Again.
水星计划
Project Mercury...
以罗马神话中的
named after the winged messenger
双翼信使为名
of the gods in Roman mythology. Today,
三年两个月又三天后的今天…
three years, two months, and three days afterwards...
“1962.2.20  约翰格伦升空”
在十次失败后，总算…
we're ready, after 10 scheduled attempts...
-好女孩
Attagirl.
我们再次尝试把美国人送上轨道
to try again to put our first man into orbit...
让约翰格伦上校进入轨道
to put Colonel John Glenn into orbit.
他会是首位进入地球轨道的美国人
Colonel John Glenn will be the first American to orbit the Earth.
各位可以看到
As you can see, there are
这里有数千人
thousands of people here today
要见证这个历史事件
to witness this historic event.
保罗，这边有问题
Paul, something's off here.
这些着陆座标跟昨天的不一样
These landing coordinates don't match yesterday's.
是IBM跑出来的结果
The IBM just ran them.
那IBM就是昨天出错了
Well, then the IBM was wrong yesterday.
对吗？
Right?
或是该死的在今天出错了
Or the damn thing's wrong today.
保罗，我说的对吗？
Paul, am I right?
看起来是这样
It appears so.
“卡纳维尔角基地”
在这之前IBM都没有问题
The IBM's been spot-on up to this point, John.
但我们会重跑一次看看
But we'll run it again, see what it comes up with.
我要老实说，艾尔
Look, I'm gonna be honest with you, Al.
我当飞行员时，是我控制机器
When I fly, I fly the machine.
现在好像是机器控制我
And right now it seems like this machine is flying me.
我们看法一致，约翰
We're on the same page, John.
我们的人在处理了
Our guys are on it.
去找那个女孩来验算
Let's get the girl to check the numbers.
那个女孩？    -对，长官
- The girl? - Yes, sir.
你是说凯萨琳？
You mean Katherine?
对，聪明的那个
Yes, sir. The smart one.
如果她说数字没问题，我就出发
I mean, she says they're good, I'm ready to go.
好，我们会去联络
All right. We'll get into it.
收到
Roger.
山姆
Sam.
去找凯萨琳哥柏
Go find Katherine Goble.
她要确认数字
She needs to verify Glenn's "Go/No-go,"
否则我们飞不了
or we're staying on the ground.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
我要找凯萨琳哥柏
I'm looking for Katherine Goble.
我现在是凯萨琳强生
It's Katherine Johnson now.
他们要你来确认座标数字
They need you to verify these coordinates.
观光客数周前就蜂拥到可可亚海滩
...and tourists have poured into Cocoa Beach for weeks.
占领了卡纳维尔角周边
Took this whole area surrounding Cape Canaveral
和佛州
and Florida, really.
全国各地，仿佛时间…
And all around the country, it's as if time...
好，给她一点空间工作
All right, give her some space. Let her work.
我们在等待格伦上校升空
...as we await Colonel John Glenn's launch.
这是美国历史性的一日
A truly historic day for America.
全国等待了好几个月
The country has waited for several months,
无人擎天神火箭测试失败多次
through many failed unmanned Atlas rocket tests
人类操纵计划也取消过10次
and 10 scheduled manned attempts...
都是因为各种机械
which were canceled for various mechanical
或系统问题
or system complications.
就连天气…
Even the weather...
最终测试与检查
All the final tests and checks
已完成
are being conducted.
约翰格伦准备登上友谊7号
John Glenn is ready to board the Friendship 7.
我们肯定
But today we remain truly optimistic,
今天是最适合起飞的日子
and it's a "Go" day in all regards.
座舱已经准备好
The capsule is ready.
火箭一切正常
The rocket itself is A-Okay,
这里的天气…
and the weather here at Cape Canaveral...
朗里那边有消息吗？    -还没
Anything from Langley? Not yet.
我们得知
We are being told
太空总署控制中心…
that Mission Control at NASA
正在最后确认
is conducting a final check of the launch
发射与返航座标
and recovery coordinates.
包括最后的返航关键点计算
Including the "Go/No-go" calculations...
这是安全
so crucial
成功发射与返航的关键
to a safe and successful launch and recovery.
多年的等待，数月的延后
After years of waiting, and months of delay,
格伦上校终于准备好这次太空飞行
Colonel Glenn is finally ready for that space flight...
我们满怀期望，等待已久
that we've been waiting for with so much anticipation.
最后确认可能暗示
These last-minute checks could indicate
太空总署的迟疑
a hesitancy on NASA's behalf.
但我们毫无保留地说
But let us say, without reservation...
约翰格伦上校的安全
that the safety of Colonel John Glenn
是首要条件
is paramount to the mission...
也是国家最重视的
and to the nation itself.
不，长官，我们还是会飞
No, sir. We're still a go.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
就是这样
That's it.
你搞什么？居然在休息？
What the devil are you doing? Are you taking a break?
♪ Yes!
♪ Say yeah
♪ Yeah
♪ Say, yeah!
“州立警局”
♪ Don't you know, we never ever
“太空总署”
♪ Never know what makes us major
♪ Your and my alchemy
♪ Yes, we can
♪ One and one equals three
♪ I feel it like lightning in the forest
♪ Yes, we can
♪ Pick a number, pick a note Harmonize the chords
♪ You're my woman don't need another
♪ Get behind the other We can lift each other
♪ It's all very well that we may never...
♪ Whoo!
现在几点？
Do you have the time?
♪ Yes, we can
♪ Like a solar system they're surrounded by you
♪ Pick a number, pick a note Harmonize the chords
♪ You're my woman don't need another
♪ Get behind the other we can lift each other
♪ ...It's all very well that we may never...
♪ Whoo!
♪ You're my woman Don't need another
♪ Get behind the other We can lift each other
♪ Whoo!
长官
Sir.
14号发射台
Pad 14.
凯萨琳
Katherine.
快点
Come on.
长官，14号发射台连线
Sir, we've got Pad 14 on the box.
好，让我跟他们说
All right. Let me in there.
这里是朗里，座标已确认
This is Langley, we have the coordinates confirmed.
待命，朗里
Stand by, Langley.
我们可以确定
We can confirm...
重返大气层的关键位置
the "Go/No-go" point for re-entry is...
是纬度16.11984
16.11984 degrees latitude...
经度-165.2356
-165.2356 degrees longitude.
发射时机确认
The launch window is a go.
着陆座标正确
The landing coordinates match.
这是很好的消息，艾尔
That is very good news, Al.
要信任看不到的东西有点困难
It's a little hard to trust something you can't look in the eyes.
没错，上校
That's right, Colonel.
凯萨琳算出来的…
Katherine did manage to calculate
还比那个大机器多几个小数点
a few decimal points further than that hunk of metal.
我会参照你的每个数字
I will take every digit you got.
帮我谢谢她
Be sure to thank her for me.
各位，火箭准备发射
Gentlemen, let's launch this rocket.
祝你好运，友谊7号
Good luck, Friendship 7.
一路顺风，朗里
Godspeed, Langley.
这里是卡纳维尔角
Here at Cape Canaveral...
继续升空倒数…
the countdown has resumed...
约翰格伦上校
as Colonel John Glenn...
登上友谊7号
is now aboard the Friendship 7...
位在14号发射台的擎天神火箭
high above the Atlas rocket on Pad 14.
高23公尺
A height of over 93 feet.
目前倒数计时…
So far, the countdown is...
这些是佛州卡纳维尔角的画面
These are pictures from Cape Canaveral, Florida.
发射台往后退了
The gantry is now moving back.
我们准备升空
We are go for launch.
水星号脱离燃料供应缆
The Mercury spacecraft umbilical is out.
倒数10秒开始
T-minus 10 seconds, and counting.
供水开始，水星号准备
Water systems, go. Mercury capsule, go.
-8、7
Eight, seven...
6、5    -引擎启动
Six, five... Ready engine. Start.
four...
3、2    -老天，一路顺风
three, two... Good Lord, ride all the way.
1、0
One, zero.
点火
Ignition.
升空
Lift off.
水星擎天神6号升空了
The M-A 6 vehicle has lifted off.
这里有点颠簸啊
It's getting a little bumpy along here.
收到，座舱指挥中心
Roger that, CAPCOM.
所有系统都在运作
All systems are reported go.
第二引擎关闭还有20秒
20 seconds to SECO.
轨道依旧完美
The trajectory is still A-Okay.
第二引擎关闭
Go for SECO.
收到，第二引擎关闭
Roger that, CAPCOM. Go for SECO.
零重力，我感觉很好
Zero G and I feel fine.
约翰格伦回报一切都好
John Glenn reports everything looks good.
这个景象太惊人了
Oh, that view is tremendous!
收到，友谊7号
Roger that, Friendship 7.
你可以进入轨道了
You are go for orbit.
谢谢，座舱指挥中心
Thank you, CAPCOM.
好，还有十个半小时
All right. Ten and a half hours to go.
如果成功绕七次的话
If we make seven round trips.
我要咖啡
I could use a coffee.
东岸时间
Well, as we approach the end of the day
接近午夜
here on the Eastern Seaboard...
格伦上校开始第三趟绕行
Colonel Glenn is just beginning his third orbit...
跨越四分之三的非洲大陆
three-quarters of the way across the African continent.
在东非尚吉巴上空可以看到…
We see he's currently over Zanzibar...
他将抵达的下一个追踪站
which is the next tracking station coming up.
感谢老天，友谊7号座舱…
Thankfully, the F riendship 7 capsule is...
新任务来了
New assignment came down the pike.
这里总是在改变
Always changing around here.
很难跟上他们
It's hard to keep up.
“太空总署IBM计算中心主管”
他们要一个长期小组
Seems like they're going to need a permanent team
负责操作IBM
to feed that IBM.
多少人？
How big of a team?
初期要30人
Thirty, to start.
谢谢你的消息，米契尔女士
Thank you for the information, Mrs. Mitchell.
不客气，范恩女士
You're quite welcome, Mrs. Vaughan.
“有色计算人员”
“热挡板”
这里出现警告灯号
We have a warning light.
座舱指挥中心7号，有警告灯号
CAPCOM 7, I have a warning light.
待命，7号
Stand by, Seven.
长官，出现警告灯号
Sir, we have a warning light.
什么情况，保罗？
What are we looking at, Paul?
热挡板可能松了
The heat shield may have come loose.
7号，请确认着陆气囊
Seven, will you confirm the landing bag
是关的吗？
is in the off position?
确定，座舱指挥中心
Affirmative, CAPCOM.
艾尔，他现在就得回来
Al, we need to get him down now.
否则他重返大气层时会被烧毁
He could burn up on re-entry.
太空里有个人
There is a man in space.
我们不想错过，所以要快
And we don't want to miss it, so we gotta hurry.
格伦出事了
Something's wrong with Glenn!
怎么回事？    -好，过来
What's going on? Come on, let's go.
快点    -你们跟着我
Come on. Hurry up, now. Y'all follow me.
“布莱萧电器”
我们刚刚得知友谊7号…
We just learned that the Friendship 7...
热挡板有脱落的危险
is in danger of losing its heat shield.
你有听到敲击的声音吗？
Have you heard any banging noises...
或是比较频繁的这种声音？
or anything of this type at higher rates?
没有，座舱指挥中心
That is a negative, CAPCOM.
这使得任务面临极大危险
This poses a grave danger to the mission.
叫他们不要抛出回航设备  叫他们不要抛出回航设备
Tell them not to jettison the retro-package.
太空总署确认
NASA is confirming there is
座舱热挡板
some sort of malfunction
可能有问题
with the capsule's heat shield...
可能会脱落
and it may not stay in place.
如果热挡板松脱
If the heat shield's loose...
回航设备的绑绳也许能固定挡板
the retro-package straps might hold it in place.
这样有用吗？
Will that work?
会有用的
It will work.
直到他到达返航位置
It will hold it until he reaches the "Go/No-go" point.
可以撑到那时候
It will work.
艾尔，他必须手动进入大气层
Al, he has to override the.05G.
就这么办
Do it.
友谊7号
Friendship 7...
我们建议你不要抛出…
we're recommending that the retro-package not...
回航设备，重复，不要抛出
I repeat, not be jettisoned.
所以你必须手动操纵重返大气层
This means that you will have to override the. 05G switch.
收到
Roger.
有原因吗？结束
Is there a reason for this? Over.
请待命，7号
Stand by, Seven.
目前没有，7号
Not at this time, Seven.
收到，指挥中心
Roger that, Command.
我会手动操纵
I will make a manual.05G entry...
收回潜望镜，结束
and bring the scope in. Over.
他知道了
He knows.
如果没有热挡板
Without a heat shield...
格伦上校不可能通过
there is no way that Colonel Glenn can get back
地球大气层
through the Earth's atmosphere.
因为温度太高了
The heat is simply too overpowering.
自动控制系统失灵
A malfunction in the automatic control system...
造成太空船倾斜飘移
is causing the spacecraft to yaw in a skid-like fashion.
使友谊7号通过大气层时
Thus putting the Friendship 7's
有危险
re-entry point in jeopardy.
此刻格伦正朝着美国俯冲
Even now, Colonel Glenn is streaking toward the United States.
他要在加州以西483公里
And he must begin the retro-sequence
开始返航
300 miles west of California...
才能在预定的回收区
if he's to reenter the atmosphere
着陆
at the designated point...
降落在佛州东南
and land in the recovery area
1,127公里处
700 miles south and east of Florida.
锁定本台了解更多详细报导
Stay tuned to this station for further details.
你要用电传飞操系统
You're going to be using fly-by-wire
重返大气层
for re-entry.
必须维持零角度，结束
You'll need to maintain a zero angle, over.
收到，切换到电传飞操
Roger. I'm on fly-by-wire.
手动操纵是备案，结束
Back it up with manual. Over.
继续和他说话
Keep talking to him.
收到
Roger.
回收区的天气
The weather, the recovery area...
浪高0.9公尺，能见度16.1公里
three foot waves, 10 miles visibility.
座舱指挥中心，我听不清楚
CAPCOM, you're going out.
他正经过通讯中断区
He's crossing the communication blackout zone.
外面有个真正的火球
There's a real fireball outside.
里面好热
It's getting a little hot in here.
座舱指挥中心，听见了吗？
CAPCOM, do you copy?
友谊7号，听得见吗？结束
Friendship 7, do you copy? Over.
再一次
Again.
友谊7号，听得见吗？结束
Friendship 7, do you copy? Over.
非常清楚，座舱指挥中心
Loud and clear, CAPCOM.
收到，你还好吗？
Roger that. How are you doing?
我很好，刚刚真的有颗火球啊
My condition is good. That was a real fireball. Boy!
收到
Roger that.
让我们带你回家吧
Let's get you all the way home.
收到
Roger that.
希望着陆点没有变
Here's hoping these landing coordinates still hold.
接近16.11984
Approaching 16.11984.
“纬度16.11984，经度-165.2356”
收到
Roger.
接近-165.2356
Approaching minus 165.2356...
倒数3、2、1
in three, two, one.
发射降落伞
Engaging chutes.
漂亮
Beautiful chute!
情况如何，座舱指挥中心？
How are we looking, CAPCOM?
你完全吻合返航点计算结果
Your "'Go/No-go" is good.
正中座标位置，7号
Landing coordinates are spot on, 7.
收到，座舱指挥中心
Roger that, CAPCOM.
我一直都想在巴哈马游泳，结束
I've always wanted to swim in the Bahamas. Over.
约翰格伦在海上降落并等待接应中
John Glenn has splashed down and he is being recovered.
感谢老天
Thank you!
约翰格伦安全降落
John Glenn has splashed down safely...
由美国海军航母接应
and is being recovered by the USS Noa.
干得好，大伙儿
Good job. Great job, guys.
凯萨琳
Katherine.
做得很好
Nice work.
您也是，哈里逊先生
You too, Mr. Harrison.
那么…
So, um...
你觉得我们能上月球吗？
you think we can get to the moon?
我们已经到那了，长官
We're already there, sir.
非常谢谢你    -谢谢您
Thank you so much. Thank you.
“约翰格伦完成三趟轨道飞行”
“约翰，做得好”
“友谊7号逆转太空竞赛的发展”
“使太空总署在1969年登陆月球”
“玛莉杰克森成为太空总署…”
“以及美国第一位非裔航太工程师”
“1979年担任朗里女性计划主持人”
“为各种肤色的女性争取发展”
各位，这是范恩女士
Girls, this is Mrs. Vaughan...
你们的主管
your supervisor.
她会告诉你们该怎么做
She'll show you how things work.
进来吧
Come on in.
“桃乐斯范恩为NASA首位非裔主管”
IBM 7090资料处理系统…
The IBM 7090 data processing system...
“她专精福传语言，掌握电子运算”
每秒能完成24,000笔乘法
is capable of solving 24,000 multiplications per second.
“是太空总署公认的顶尖人才之一”
“太空科技  史塔佛与凯萨琳强生着”
“凯萨琳继续计算…”
“阿波罗登月任务与太空梭计划”
“太空总署以凯萨琳计算大楼…”
“纪念她对太空旅行的突破性贡献”
“她在97岁时获颁总统自由奖章”
“并庆祝与吉姆强生结褵56年”
“太空任务团队”
“凯萨琳强生”
“桃乐斯范恩”
“玛莉杰克森”
♪ They'll call it a mystery
“太空总署朗里研究中心”
♪ But we're gonna call it Victory
♪ We'll be writing history
♪ It's gonna be
♪ Victory
♪ They'll be signs on top of signs
♪ Just so you know the
♪ History
♪ It's saying victory
♪ Is with me
♪ Oh, let them laugh about it
♪ Don't worry what the doubter's saying
♪ Yes, it's an uphill battle
♪ But guess who else is playin '
♪ The next time y'all in action
♪ And the ghost is in the room
♪ Watch you work through the masses
♪ You know that we've been used
♪ Don't let it be
♪ No matter how deep
♪ I swear just believe
♪ You'll find victory
♪ Find your victory
♪ They'll call it a mystery
♪ But we're gonna call it
♪ Victory
♪ We'll be writing history
♪ It's gonna be
♪ Victory
♪ They'll be signs on top of signs
♪ Just so you know the
♪ History
♪ It's saying victory
♪ Is with me
♪ The Bible says you should pray for nothing
♪ 'Cause every week it's gonna be something
♪ You know the devil can't wait to jump in
♪ And complicate the things you trust in
♪ But I know my foundation
♪ Is solid and can take some hating
♪ Prayer's gon' be on this space station
♪ On the way to the master's apron
♪ They'll call it a mystery
♪ Victory
♪ We'll be writing history
♪ It's gon' be
♪ Victory
♪ It's saying victory
♪ Is with me
♪ Hey!
♪ Oh
♪ When I first got here
♪ I defined my way
♪ But the end of the days were dark
♪ When I was not clear
♪ You showed me my mistakes
♪ But told me keep the pace Don't get lost
♪ So should I not fear, yeah
♪ That's how it feels when you love me
♪ And you're my sightseer
♪ 'Cause before I'm in a rut
♪ You multiply by 10 times what they took from me
♪ You send out a branch from the longest tree
♪ When I'm in quicksand
♪ But in my mind it's really your arm to me
♪ Can't believe it, what a lift and hard to believe
♪ Surrender But there's a difference
♪ Surrender, surrender
♪ 'Cause I understand Explain to me
♪ There's no coincidence
♪ Just confirmation
♪ Let me see them hands
♪ I was down on myself
♪ And I called you
♪ And your answer is "What can I do?"
♪ So much you do for me
♪ In the sound of my breath seen all the years
♪ Of surrender
♪ Just know I'm here
♪ Reporting for duty
♪ When it feel this good Don't ever let go, go
♪ Don't ever let go, oh
♪ Hard to believe
♪ Surrender but there's a difference
♪ Surrender, surrender
♪ 'Cause I understand Explain to me
♪ There's no coincidence
♪ Just confirmation
♪ Let me see them hands
♪ Please, just wave
♪ Wave, wave
♪ Wave, wave Wave
♪ In this place
♪ Just wave Wave
♪ Wave your hands
♪ Wave, wave
♪ Try to understand the way I've been behaving
♪ It's a funny thing you really gotta see
♪ Is it just your love that's got me going crazy?
♪ Or are my eyes playing with me
♪ All day your love just comes shining down
♪ Just like the sweetest bees
♪ I feel you from my root to my crown
♪ It's mighty good to me Like caramel
♪ He's right beside me
♪ My mind's his carousel
♪ It's how he rides me
♪ So there's no parallels
♪ Y'all know me very well
♪ It's yellow lightning
♪ Try to understand the way I've been behaving
♪ It's a funny thing you really gotta see
♪ Is it just your love that's got me going crazy
♪ Or are my eyes playing with me
♪ Just like a mirage
♪ I love you like you were gold
♪ Gold, gold
♪ And I'm sorry, baby
♪ For the what ifs, maybes
♪ I've taken too far
♪ I know I must be looking crazy
♪ I'm sorry, baby
♪ For the what ifs, maybes
♪ I take it too far
♪ You know I must be looking crazy
♪ Try to understand the way I've been behaving
♪ It's a funny thing you really gotta see
♪ Is it just your love that's got me going crazy
♪ Or are my eyes playing with me
♪ I spent many nights on my knees praying
♪ From the side effects of all this heat
♪ But I'm telling y'all it does feel amazing
♪ Or are my eyes playing with me